<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The Spanish rogue as it was acted by His Majesties servants / written by Tho. Duffett.</title>
            <author>Duffett, Thomas.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1674</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 170 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 41 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B21422</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing D2453</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12331272</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12331272</idno>
            <idno type="VID">199207</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B21422)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 199207)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 209:8)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The Spanish rogue as it was acted by His Majesties servants / written by Tho. Duffett.</title>
                  <author>Duffett, Thomas.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 71, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for William Cademan ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1674.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Errata on p. [1] at end.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-01</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-01</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:199207:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:199207:1"/>
            <p>THE SPANISH ROGUE.</p>
            <p>As it was ACTED BY HIS Majeſties Servants.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Written by THO: D<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>FFETT.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Hor. Serm.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <l>— O bone! ne te</l>
               <l>Fruſtrere: Inſanis &amp; tu, Stultique prope omnes.</l>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>William Cademan</hi> at the <hi>Pope</hi>'s <hi>Head</hi> in the <hi>Lower Walk</hi> in the <hi>New Exchange</hi> in the <hi>Strand.</hi> 
               <abbr>M.DC.LXXIV.</abbr>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:199207:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:199207:2"/>
            <head>TO MADAM <hi>ELLEN G<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>YN.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Madam,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is not, becauſe you were pleas'd to be very kind to this Play, when it was act<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; for I know not whether you ever honour'd it with your Preſence: Nor is it to return you a troubleſome acknowledgment for Favours; for I am ſure you do not know me: Nor the hope of obliging you to my future ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage; for the utmoſt return I expect is your pardon; None of theſe has made me guilty of this preſumption. But ſince a Play in print, without an Epiſtle Dedicatory, is now like a Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſh Gallant without a Miſtriſs, or a Papiſt with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out
<pb facs="tcp:199207:3"/> a tutelar Saint, I reſolv'd to obey Cuſtom in making a Dedication, and my own free inclinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in the choice of your Excellent Self, at whoſe Feet I humbly lay this; wherein, though my raſh Boldneſs may be cenſur'd, I'm ſure my Prudence will be applauded: For if this Cenſorious Age will ſubmit to the moſt perfect Beauty, or the greateſt Goodneſs in the World, under your Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection it will be ſafe.—Nature almoſt overcome by Art, has in your Self rally'd all her ſcatter'd Forces, and on your charming Brow, ſits ſmiling at the ſlaviſh toyls which yours and her envious Foes endure; ſtriving in vain with the fading weak ſupplies of Art, to rival your Beauties; which are ever the ſame, and alwayes incomparable. Notwithſtanding this great Truth is celebrated by All that know you; You ſtill are Miſtriſs of ſo much obliging Affability, ſo free from ſullen Pride, and affected Statelineſs, the uſual Atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dants of extraordinary Felicity; not contented to be ſafe in the barren praiſe of doing no ill, but ſo readily and ſo frequently doing good, as if it were not your Nature, but your Buſineſs; that, next to your Beauty, theſe Virtues are the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt
<pb facs="tcp:199207:3"/> Miracle of the Age. If I am the firſt that has taken the boldneſs to tell you this, in Print, 'tis becauſe <hi>I</hi> am more ambitious than all others, to be known by the Title of,</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Madam,</salute>
               <signed>Your Admirer, and humbleſt Servant, <hi>T. D.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="dramatis_personae">
            <pb facs="tcp:199207:4"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:199207:4"/>
            <head>The Perſons Names.</head>
            <list>
               <item>Don Feniſe—<hi>Mr.</hi> Harris.</item>
               <item>Don Alonzo—<hi>Mr.</hi> Lyddal.</item>
               <item>Don Manuel—<hi>Mr.</hi> Watſon.</item>
               <item>Laraſco—<hi>Mr.</hi> Powell.</item>
               <item>Mingo—<hi>Mr.</hi> Caſh.</item>
               <item>Sanchez—<hi>Mr.</hi> Griffin.</item>
               <item>Alcinda—<hi>Mrs.</hi> Boutell.</item>
               <item>Roſella—<hi>Mrs.</hi> Uphill.</item>
               <item>Tereſa—<hi>Mrs.</hi> Corye.</item>
               <item>Leonella—<hi>Mrs.</hi> Kneppe.</item>
               <item>Neighbours, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
         <div type="prologue">
            <pb facs="tcp:199207:5"/>
            <head>PROLOGUE</head>
            <byline>Spoken by Mrs. BOUTELL.</byline>
            <lg>
               <l>O<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>R poor forſaken Stage does now appear,</l>
               <l>Like ſome cast Miſtriſs that has once been fair:</l>
               <l>In ev'ry part a ſad decay we find,</l>
               <l>Yet fondly look, that you ſhould ſtill be kind;</l>
               <l>At least we hope, what our Defects deny,</l>
               <l>Your eager want will at this time ſupply:</l>
               <l>For, as fierce Captain that from Camp returns,</l>
               <l>Flies at each Vizard-mask he ſees,— and burns:</l>
               <l>So, in this Dearth of Wit, methinks to Night</l>
               <l>You ſhould not ſtand to mind if all be right.</l>
               <l>None ſure will rail at faults we Women make,</l>
               <l>When the kind failing's onely for your ſake.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>And, tell me Gallants! which would you like best?</l>
               <l>The tedious Fool that ſtayes 'till ſhe is drest,</l>
               <l>Or the kind Girl, who when the hour is come,</l>
               <l>Slips on the Morning Gown, and ſteals from home?</l>
               <l>After the good old Engliſh way we treat,</l>
               <l>Though it be plain, we give you wholeſom Meat.</l>
               <l>Our Friends of th' other Houſe, do often take ye</l>
               <l>With ſuch Ragouſts as naſty French Cooks make ye.</l>
               <l>With garniſh'd Diſhes they delight your Eyes,</l>
               <l>And give you nought but Vermine in diſguiſe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>'Tis not a Ladies Paint, can gain her Hearts,</l>
               <l>Nor ſilly Lords fine Cloaths, can mend his Parts:</l>
               <l>Loaded with Liv'ries, the Gilt Coach may roul,</l>
               <l>And yet the Spark within may be a Fool.</l>
               <l>To your own Cost, most of you Gallants know,</l>
               <l>That is not alwayes best that makes a Show.</l>
               <l>Were the Truth known, here's many a Spark I fear,</l>
               <l>That has been lewdly Chous'd in fine Semar.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Thus Fools are caught, but the old crafty Sinner,</l>
               <l>Takes the ſound Wench; though in Straw-Hat and Pinner.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="dialogue">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:199207:5"/>
            <head>THE Spaniſh Rogue.</head>
            <div n="1" type="act">
               <head>ACT I.</head>
               <div n="1" type="scene">
                  <head>Scene 1.</head>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Enter</hi> Don Feniſe <hi>and</hi> Laraſco <hi>in</hi> Feniſe<hi>'s Houſe.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fen.</speaker>
                     <l>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">D</seg>Eſpairing Merchants, when their Fleets appear,</l>
                     <l>After the dangers of a ſtormy year,</l>
                     <l>Have ſwelling hopes like mine; yet doubt their Fate,</l>
                     <l>'Till in their greedy arms they hug their freight.</l>
                     <l>Aſſiſt me Fortune! fix thy rouling wheel</l>
                     <l>Some few ſhort minutes, and for ever reel.</l>
                     <l>Not yet! — how dull and lazily it creeps? <stage>Looks on his Watch.</stage>
                     </l>
                     <l>O Expectation! how each moment ſleeps!</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Lar.</speaker>
                     <l>Sleep on, old time! for thou haſt need of Reſt,</l>
                     <l>Who art for ev'ry Lovers ſervice preſt.</l>
                     <l>Had my grave Courage been as raſh as his,</l>
                     <l>We both had ſlep'd eternally ere this.</l>
                     <l>Theſe Lovers; whom the Devil cannot frigh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>,</l>
                     <l>When near enjoyment fires their appetite;</l>
                     <l>Deſign'd to meet like Cats, i'th dead of night:</l>
                     <l>But I told him, whom nothing elſe cou'd ſtay,</l>
                     <l>'Twas her command he ſhould not ſtir till day.</l>
                     <l>This time much better fits my peaceful mind,</l>
                     <l>Though Love wo'nt, let them ſee, muſt I be blind?</l>
                     <l>She has, poor thing! expected him all night,</l>
                     <l>And, though he's freed from's peeviſh Miſtriſs by't,</l>
                     <l>I know he'll Rant; but my reſolve is ſet —</l>
                     <l>Theſe valiant Friends did never fail me yet. <stage>His Feet.</stage>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <pb n="2" facs="tcp:199207:6"/>
                     <speaker>Fen.</speaker>
                     <l>Ev'n in conſent, ſhe's cruel too, the night</l>
                     <l>Much better wou'd diſguiſe a Lovers flight.</l>
                     <l>None but her ſelf can ſuch delayes repair;</l>
                     <l>Impatience is as reſtleſs as deſpair. —</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Exeunt</hi> Feniſe <hi>and</hi> Laraſco.</stage>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="scene">
                  <head>Scene 2.</head>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Enter</hi> Alcinda <hi>and</hi> Leonella <hi>in</hi> Don Manuel<hi>'s Hall.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Alc.</speaker>
                     <l>Is this a Lovers haſte? Did he not ſay,</l>
                     <l>Each minute in my abſence ſeem'd a day?</l>
                     <l>Falſe man! unworthy of my meaneſt thought!</l>
                     <l>To ſlight a Love he has ſo dearly bought —</l>
                     <l>My flame increaſes by his cold delay;</l>
                     <l>Revenge ſhall lead me off, though love wou'd ſtay. <stage>
                           <hi>Exit</hi> Alcinda.</stage>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Leon.</speaker>
                     <l>The language of thoſe begging eyes I know,</l>
                     <l>Implores a reaſon that ſhe may not go:</l>
                     <l>I'll rather make her hate him if I can,</l>
                     <l>For ſhe's too good for ſuch a faithleſs man. —</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Going out, ſhe ſees</hi> Feniſe <hi>and</hi> Laraſeo <hi>coming; and returns with a dark Lanthorn.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Enter</hi> Feniſe <hi>and</hi> Laraſco.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fen.</speaker>
                     <l>The King of Planets from his daz'ling Crown,</l>
                     <l>With more than common Red gilds ore the Town:</l>
                     <l>Bluſhing to ſee Loves ſecrets truſt the Light.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Leon.</speaker>
                     <l>Stand! Who goes there? what ſturdy mortal Wight,</l>
                     <l>When diſmal ſhades the ſleeping World oreſpread,</l>
                     <l>And yawning Graves let out their wandring dead,</l>
                     <l>Diſturbs the ſilent night? and raſhly pryes</l>
                     <l>Into pale <hi>Hecates</hi> drowſie ſacrifice!</l>
                     <l>Speak daring Mortal! ſay, what makes thee creep</l>
                     <l>Through unknown paths, when time itſelf's aſleep?</l>
                     <l>Declare thy dire intent —</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fen.</speaker>
                     <l>Let's make all ſure,</l>
                     <l>And play theſe Frolicks when we are ſecure.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <pb n="3" facs="tcp:199207:6"/>
                     <speaker>Leon.</speaker>
                     <l>This voyce I know; deceive me not pale Moon!</l>
                     <l>'Tis he! — hey ho! what made you come ſo ſoon?</l>
                     <l>This Love's a reſtleſs Bedfellow; take heed,</l>
                     <l>Tread ſoft and ſure; this ſhews you love indeed,</l>
                     <l>T' adventure out this dreadful ſtormy Night,</l>
                     <l>You might have taken cold, or met a Spright —</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Lar.</speaker>
                     <l>A Spright! where! where!</l>
                     <l>Ah good Sir! dear Sir! ſtay no longer here —</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fen.</speaker>
                     <l>Pry'thee releaſe my patience, I'll approve</l>
                     <l>This ſport another time — But where's my Love?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Leon.</speaker>
                     <l>Where is your Love indeed? to make her wait,</l>
                     <l>Were it not loſt, you had not come ſo late.</l>
                     <l>Go boaſt your Treachery, and then declare</l>
                     <l>How long you woo'd, how oft you perjur'd are;</l>
                     <l>When you conſult your Conqueſt, ſum your Coſt</l>
                     <l>Of precious time, and Oaths; See who has loſt.</l>
                     <l>She will your ſcorn with intereſt return,</l>
                     <l>And, for your falſeneſs, Heav'n will make you mourn.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fen.</speaker>
                     <l>Thy Looks are well, but in thy Words I find</l>
                     <l>The certain ſigns of a diſtemper'd mind;</l>
                     <l>Is it to me you ſpeak? and can you prove</l>
                     <l>My wandring Faith, or my decaying Love?</l>
                     <l>Diſperſe theſe wonders which your words create;</l>
                     <l>It was my Penance to attend ſo late;</l>
                     <l>And if I ſuffer, for your own deſigne,</l>
                     <l>Your loud Complaints more juſtly will be mine.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Leon.</speaker>
                     <l>Ah Sir! Excuſes which ſo weak appear,</l>
                     <l>Betray too little Love, or too much Fear:</l>
                     <l>Do jealous Lovers, which abhor the light,</l>
                     <l>Call <hi>Phoebus</hi> to atteſt their ſecret flight?</l>
                     <l>She ſummon'd you ere Night wax'd grey, as ſoon</l>
                     <l>As the <hi>Antipodes</hi> enjoy'd their Noon.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fen.</speaker>
                     <l>Thou heartleſs Fool! what miſchief haſt thou done,</l>
                     <l>Inſtructing me to wait the riſing Sun;</l>
                     <l>Kneel to good Fortune, for thy Life's the ſtake;</l>
                     <l>Raiſe not my Ruine on this Rogues miſtake,</l>
                     <l>I'll lead her hence, or periſh at her feet.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Leon.</speaker>
                     <l>Sooner the Eve and Infant day may meet;</l>
                     <pb n="4" facs="tcp:199207:7"/>
                     <l>This injury reviv'd her dying ſcorn,</l>
                     <l>And ſtay'd me here to haſten your return.</l>
                     <l>Ill Tydings flie, too ſoon you'll hear the reſt —</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fen.</speaker>
                     <l>The reſt! Can my Misfortune be increaſt?</l>
                     <l>I know too little, ſince there's more behind.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Leon.</speaker>
                     <p>If ſhe can hate you, to your ſelf be kind.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fen.</speaker>
                     <p>Villain be gone! thy ſwifteſt fears out-flie —</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Leon.</speaker>
                     <p>Your Sword would bluſh to wear ſo baſe a Die.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fen.</speaker>
                     <l>In ſuch extremes of Fate, I want a guide:</l>
                     <l>None can ſecurely ſtem wild paſſions Tyde.</l>
                     <l>Proceed! — hold! — (curs'd fortune) diſpatch the reſt —</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Leon.</speaker>
                     <p>Y'are baniſh'd from her preſence, and her breſt.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fen.</speaker>
                     <l>His baſeneſs is too weak a guard — He dyes!</l>
                     <l>For ſuch a Saint too poor a Sacrifice.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Feniſe <hi>draws, and</hi> Laraſco <hi>runs in crying.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Lar.</speaker>
                     <l>Dear! Dear! merciful! pardon my miſtake,</l>
                     <l>For Heavens, Oh Sir! for fair <hi>Alcinda's</hi> ſake — <stage>
                           <hi>Within. Exit</hi> Laraſco.</stage>
                     </l>
                     <l>Murther! Murther! I'm dead! I'm dead!</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fen.</speaker>
                     <p>Nothing to ſtop his Throat? no hearty Curſe?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Leon.</speaker>
                     <l>O for an <hi>Iriſh</hi> Wolf to make him hoarſe.</l>
                     <l>Thieves! Thieves! Thieves! Rogues! Villains! Dogs! Thieves!</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Manuel <hi>within.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Leon.</speaker>
                     <p>The Blood-hounds up, no cunning can relieves.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fen.</speaker>
                     <p>Curſe on his yelping Jaws! what ſhall we do?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Leon.</speaker>
                     <p>Here, here! quickly Sir, ſtep in here —</p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Exeunt</hi> Mingo <hi>and</hi> Leonella.</stage>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Enter</hi> Don Manuel <hi>in a ridiculous Morning dreſs.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Man.</speaker>
                     <l>Thieves! Thieves! Wife! Daughter! Maid! no body hear?</l>
                     <l>All the dores open, undone! rob'd! undone!</l>
                     <l>All the World aſleep? am I heard by none?</l>
                     <l>Murther! murther! I'm dead, down right ſtone dead.</l>
                     <l>Ha! 'tis ſo, 'tis ſo, my wild girls are fled.</l>
                     <l>Pray Heav'n it be no worſe, I'll raiſe the Town.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Exit</hi> Manuel <hi>locking the dore after him.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <stage>
                     <pb n="5" facs="tcp:199207:7"/>
                     <hi>Enter</hi> Don Feniſe <hi>and</hi> Leonella.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Leon.</speaker>
                     <l>Conſult her ſafety, though you ſlight your own;</l>
                     <l>Her Honour ſuffers in your longer ſtay,</l>
                     <l>No dull conſideration; but away —</l>
                     <l>Still more unhappy! he has lock'd the dore.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Exit</hi> Leonella.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fen.</speaker>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Never to ſee, nor think of me no more!</l>
                        <l>Why can ſhe not my Love transform to hate?</l>
                        <l>And rule my Paſſion, as ſhe rules my Fate?</l>
                        <l>Why did thoſe mighty Powers we adore,</l>
                        <l>Give Beauty ſo much ſtrength, and give no more?</l>
                        <l>Have I for this, outwatch'd a Tyrants Spie?</l>
                        <l>A Hermits Zeal, or Stateſmans Jealouſie?</l>
                        <l>When Mad-men ſleep, and madder Chymiſts reſt,</l>
                        <l>Loves greater madneſs ſtill annoyes my Breſt.</l>
                        <l>Repent! too cruel Fair thy Vow repent!</l>
                        <l>Let the Offender bear the puniſhment —</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Unkind <hi>Alcinda!</hi> Muſt we ever part?</l>
                        <l>Can She ſo eaſily command her heart?</l>
                        <l>To my inſulting Fate too much I bow:</l>
                        <l>If I muſt never more, I'll ſee her now —</l>
                        <l>I dare not go; Dull <hi>Feniſe!</hi> canſt thou bear</l>
                        <l>Theſe injuries from Love, and blame his fear?</l>
                        <l>He's innocent, or thou muſt guilty prove;</l>
                        <l>As he to fear ſubmits, thou yeild'ſt to Love.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Enter</hi> Leonella <hi>pulling</hi> Laraſco <hi>in.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Leon.</speaker>
                     <p>Among the Women you can domineer —</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Lar.</speaker>
                     <p>Kill me Sir! Kill me! rid me of my fear.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fen.</speaker>
                     <l>This Fellow may his frighten'd ſenſe regain,</l>
                     <l>The Object once remov'd, removes his pain;</l>
                     <l>Love, like an angry Ghoſt, allows no reſt,</l>
                     <l>But ſtill torments the guilty Lovers Breſt.</l>
                     <l>Yet I'll ſhak't off!<note n="*" place="margin">
                           <hi>Alcinda</hi> at a Window.</note> Ha! 'tis ſhe! treacherous ſenſe!</l>
                     <l>A Thouſand Devils cannot force me hence.</l>
                     <pb n="6" facs="tcp:199207:8"/>
                     <l>Urge it no more, but to her lead the way.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Leon.</speaker>
                     <p>Her ſtrict Commands I dare not diſobey.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fen.</speaker>
                     <l>The ſaddeſt proſpect of my Fate I ſee,</l>
                     <l>She being loſt, much worſe it cannot be.</l>
                     <l>Thou ſhalt relent — here's gold —</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Leon.</speaker>
                     <l>Who can reſiſt the charms your tongue affords?</l>
                     <l>This is a language ſweeter far than words.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Lar.</speaker>
                     <l>O Wondrous Virtue of imperious gold!</l>
                     <l>For thee is Honour bought, and Heaven ſold.</l>
                     <l>Yet, had I all ere fruitful <hi>Peru</hi> bred,</l>
                     <l>I'd give it freely to be ſafe in Bed.</l>
                     <l>What new deſign? ſomething ſhe talks of me,</l>
                     <l>I fear ſome plot upon my Chaſtity.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fen.</speaker>
                     <p>Sirrah! Obſerve her Orders —</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Lar.</speaker>
                     <p>More Catterwouling yet! Hell ſtop her breath!</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fen.</speaker>
                     <p>Another Murmur ſhall foretel thy death.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Lar.</speaker>
                     <l>I wiſh'd a task, whoſe danger might declare</l>
                     <l>What I dare do, my Folly to repair.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Leon.</speaker>
                     <l>Watch, and inform us when he comes, See right,</l>
                     <l>Let not your ſhadow put you in a fright.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Lar.</speaker>
                     <p>I'll fight the proudeſt he that wears a head.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Leon.</speaker>
                     <l>What dareſt thou ſtake againſt my Maidenhead?</l>
                     <l>I do not take thy ruſty Sword away.</l>
                     <l>Thou a Fighter!</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Lar.</speaker>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Donna!</hi> your beauty may,</l>
                     <l>That man is mad that will with Women fight,</l>
                     <l>Your loſs by day you can revenge at night.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fen.</speaker>
                     <l>Diſpatch his charge, my deareſt blood I'd pay</l>
                     <l>To buy each minute which you throw away.</l>
                     <l>Villain! be watchful — <stage>
                           <hi>Exeunt</hi> Feniſe <hi>and</hi> Leonella.</stage>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Lar.</speaker>
                     <l>Sir! I will — not ſtay —</l>
                     <l>If all my art and ſtrength can get away.</l>
                     <l>This Lock is vengeance ſtrong, No paſſage here:</l>
                     <l>No Window big enough for creeping Fear?</l>
                     <l>Ne'r talk on't! I can't endure to be kill'd,</l>
                     <l>He cares not ſo his wild deſire's fulfill'd.</l>
                     <l>I'll try the Garden wall — is this door faſt?</l>
                     <l>Then life adieu! the fatal Die is caſt.</l>
                     <pb n="7" facs="tcp:199207:8"/>
                     <l>A Kingdom to ſecure my life! — he's there!<stage>A Noiſe within.</stage>
                     </l>
                     <l>Oh my dear pretty heart! thy end draws near.</l>
                     <l>O Death what ſhall I do? where ſhall I hide?</l>
                     <l>No cunning place to tye my ſelf aſide!</l>
                     <l>A little ſtay — my knife! yet do not come: —</l>
                     <l>Pox on't! now I have left my knife at home:</l>
                     <l>Elſe I could cut my throat. Poor carkaſs! how</l>
                     <l>Muſt thou be Slic'd and Carbonado'd now?</l>
                     <l>I might have ſtop'd the Lock too, fool that I was!</l>
                     <l>Oh my belly! good Lock don't let him paſs!</l>
                     <l>Dear Lock ſtand too't! ſweet Lock don't let 'em come!</l>
                     <l>'Wounds! how I ſhall be Slaſh'd? there's forty o'm —</l>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>Enter</hi> Don Manuel <hi>and Neighbours ridiculouſly arm'd; They ſee</hi> Laraſco, <hi>and run off again.</hi>
                     </stage>
                     <l>So, ſo, now they conſult about my End —</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Enter again</hi> Don Manuel <hi>and Neighbours.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Man.</speaker>
                     <l>You that ſuch daring courage did pretend,</l>
                     <l>What made you run? I'll bravely go before,</l>
                     <l>Come Neighbours! enter all, and ſhut the dore.</l>
                     <l>What all gone agen? my caſe is hard, <stage>Laraſco <hi>ſtands up like a Statue.</hi>
                        </stage>
                     </l>
                     <l>I dare not ſee, my houſe without a guard.</l>
                     <l>Ha! one of the Villains! or but a ſhape</l>
                     <l>Set up to fright me, while the Rogues eſcape;</l>
                     <l>It does not move, nor breath, it muſt be ſo —</l>
                     <l>Were it a Man, thus wou'd I forward go —</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Lar.</speaker>
                     <p>Now muſt I go to Pot! — how my bones ake!— <stage>Aſide.</stage>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Man.</speaker>
                     <l>And Slaſh him thus, — ha! did not ſomething ſhake?</l>
                     <l>What ſhall a Scarecrow make me thus afraid?</l>
                     <l>Yet, by this light! 'tis very neatly made;</l>
                     <l>Subſtance! true mortal ſubſtance too!— I'le ſwear,</l>
                     <l>Not one convenient member wanting here.</l>
                     <l>This ſhape may any maid alive deceive —</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Lar.</speaker>
                     <l>I am a very Image I believe,</l>
                     <l>But I have heard that Images can't feel. <stage>Aſide.</stage>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Man.</speaker>
                     <l>I fear no fleſh alive, by this bright ſteel!</l>
                     <pb n="8" facs="tcp:199207:9"/>
                     <l>O for a <hi>Caeſar</hi> now, or for that brave</l>
                     <l>Undaunted Soul that did the world enſlave;</l>
                     <l>Like Tennis-balls I'd whirl them about,</l>
                     <l>And thus make way to let their Courage out <stage>
                           <hi>He ſtrikes</hi> Laraſco.</stage>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Lar.</speaker>
                     <p>Oh! Curſe on your valour! — <stage>Aſide.</stage>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Man.</speaker>
                     <l>I'll try to place</l>
                     <l>His head upright, and paint ſome red in's face.</l>
                     <l>The noſe too ſhould be mended, and the eyes —</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Lar.</speaker>
                     <l>How to eſcape this dog I can't deviſe —</l>
                     <l>Now he has turn'd his back, I'le cut his throat —</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Laraſco <hi>draws,</hi> Manuel <hi>ſees him, and runs off; then</hi> Laraſco <hi>falls grov'ling on the ground.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Man.</speaker>
                     <p>Murther! murther! murther!</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Lar.</speaker>
                     <p>Oh diſmal note!</p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Enter</hi> Leonella <hi>haſtily.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Leon.</speaker>
                     <p>What noiſe was that? what's the diſturbance here?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Lar.</speaker>
                     <l>Mercy! good Sir, Mercy! Oh do but hear,</l>
                     <l>I'll confeſs all — Noble <hi>Don Manuel!</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Your curſed Wench, by ſome infernal Spell</l>
                     <l>Entic'd <hi>Don Feniſe</hi> hither, and has ſold</l>
                     <l>The fair <hi>Alcinda</hi> to him for his gold.</l>
                     <l>He's now within perſuading her away;</l>
                     <l>I am a ſervant, Sir, — forc'd to obey —</l>
                     <l>Dear Sir be merciful!</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Leon.</speaker>
                     <p>Riſe, and be free —</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Lar.</speaker>
                     <l>Ha! is it you? confound ſuch Sorcerie!</l>
                     <l>The Hall's inchanted, or this cou'd not be.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Enter</hi> Feniſe <hi>and</hi> Alcinda.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fen.</speaker>
                     <l>Since that bleſt hour I gave my heart to you,</l>
                     <l>My buſie thoughts no other object knew.</l>
                     <l>My Eyes ne'r ſtray'd to any other face,</l>
                     <l>My heart ne'r fram'd a wiſh beyond this place.</l>
                     <l>I plead no merit, Madam! for I know</l>
                     <l>My Service weak, and my deſert too low.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <pb n="9" facs="tcp:199207:9"/>
                     <speaker>Alcin.</speaker>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Feniſe!</hi> Upbraid me not with your deſert,</l>
                     <l>I know 'tis great, and well deſerves my heart;</l>
                     <l>Were you unworthy, my obliging Vow</l>
                     <l>Has made me yours, nor will I break it now.</l>
                     <l>Yet Gratitude (for Love ne'r reach'd my Breſt,</l>
                     <l>Nor yet had power to diſturb my reſt)</l>
                     <l>Makes me your Pris'ner now; and let<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>s me ſee,</l>
                     <l>You prize your fading pleaſures more than me.</l>
                     <l>Your ſatisfaction you reſolve to buy,</l>
                     <l>Though at the price of my dear liberty.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fen.</speaker>
                     <l>By what you want, judge not the love I have,</l>
                     <l>You cannot be a Pris'ner to your Slave.</l>
                     <l>If Love cannot incite you to depart,</l>
                     <l>Truſt gratitude awhile to guide your heart.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Alc.</speaker>
                     <l>Give Reaſon yours, and an Example ſhew,</l>
                     <l>Or ask no more what you refuſe to do.</l>
                     <l>You cannot ceaſe to Love; I can't begin;</l>
                     <l>You cannot break the Snare, nor I get in;</l>
                     <l>Yet, to content your ſelf, you'll puniſh me —</l>
                     <l>Alas! this is not Love, but Cruelty.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fen.</speaker>
                     <l>How ſtrangely Madam! at the ſelf-ſame time,</l>
                     <l>You do excuſe, and charge me with a Crime.</l>
                     <l>If Love can't be compell'd, as 'tis moſt true,</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Feniſe</hi> adores, but Fortune injures you.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Alc.</speaker>
                     <l>Juſtly your Paſſion may ſuſpected grow,</l>
                     <l>Since you demand thoſe proofs you dare not ſhow.</l>
                     <l>You gain my Faith by leaving me behind,</l>
                     <l>Leſſen your Love, and practiſe to be kind.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Leon.</speaker>
                     <l>Tempt not your Deſtiny, but let's be gone,</l>
                     <l>Her wandring Fancy muſt return anon:</l>
                     <l>Madam! if you will go, let's haſte away,</l>
                     <l>To flie thoſe Dangers which attend your ſtay.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Alc.</speaker>
                     <p>Thou know'ſt my heart, let <hi>Feniſe</hi> be our Guide —</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Leon.</speaker>
                     <p>Spread all your Sails, you have the Wind and Tide.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Alc.</speaker>
                     <p>What Noiſe is that?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>A Noiſe at the dore.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Leon.</speaker>
                     <l>This comes of your delay —</l>
                     <l>O Heav'ns! <hi>Don Manuel</hi> has ſtop'd your way.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <pb n="10" facs="tcp:199207:10"/>
                     <speaker>Alc.</speaker>
                     <p>What will <hi>Don Feniſe</hi> do? perſuade him in.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Lar.</speaker>
                     <p>Now does my ſtorm of miſery begin.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Alc.</speaker>
                     <l>Haſte to the Garden, there's a private dore.</l>
                     <l>Ah <hi>Feniſe!</hi> now we part to meet no more.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Lar.</speaker>
                     <p>Sweet Maſter! Dear Maſter!</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Alc.</speaker>
                     <p>Once more farewel! <stage>
                           <hi>Exeunt</hi> Alcinda <hi>and</hi> Leonella.</stage>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Lar.</speaker>
                     <l>Pray! pray for us! — Now Toll the Paſſing bell —</l>
                     <l>Oh that I had but dy'd, Ten years before</l>
                     <l>My Mothers onely hopeful Son was bore:</l>
                     <l>I had been car'd for, I had happy been,</l>
                     <l>This Catterwouling I had never ſeen.</l>
                     <l>Will you be murther'd in your Muſe? Dye here!</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fen.</speaker>
                     <l>It muſt be ſo, this ſhews my Love ſo clear,</l>
                     <l>She can no more deny me —</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Lar.</speaker>
                     <l>What, more heroick Tricks? — Oh how I ſhake!</l>
                     <l>Is this a time for Love, when Life's at ſtake?</l>
                     <l>Now will he dye to ſhew this Cat his heart—</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fen.</speaker>
                     <l>She knows I may compel her to depart;</l>
                     <l>And now, juſt at this time, to let her ſtay—</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Enter</hi> Don Manuel <hi>and his Friends.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Man.</speaker>
                     <p>Here be the Rogues, Now Neighbours kill and ſlay —</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Lar.</speaker>
                     <l>How fierce and big the Suck-bloods look? I'll ſpread</l>
                     <l>My Carkaſs on the ground, and ſay I'm dead. <stage>Laraſco <hi>lies down.</hi>
                        </stage>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fen.</speaker>
                     <l>Her Vows I'll give her back, and when ſhe's free,</l>
                     <l>Juſtice will bind her to love none but me.</l>
                     <l>Since all my Vows ſo unſucceſsful prove,</l>
                     <l>That even yet you ſeem to doubt my Love:</l>
                     <l>I hope this ſingle Act will make it plain,</l>
                     <l>Here <hi>Feniſe</hi> gives you back your ſelf again —</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Man.</speaker>
                     <p>How's this? <hi>Don Feniſe!</hi> ſure it cannot be —</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fen.</speaker>
                     <l>Ha! where is <hi>Alcinda?</hi> what's this I ſee?</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Laraſco</hi> murther'd by theſe Cowards Swords!</l>
                     <l>This Tempeſt muſt not be allay'd with words.</l>
                     <l>Have at your hearts; lie there; are you ſo quick?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>One falls as kill'd;</hi> Manuel <hi>and the reſt flie,</hi> Feniſe <hi>purſues them.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Lar.</speaker>
                     <l>Oh my poor heart! I'm very ſtomack ſick.</l>
                     <pb n="11" facs="tcp:199207:10"/>
                     <l>Are they all gone? this was a brave Deſign;</l>
                     <l>Cowardly Rogues! to ſtrike a Man behind —</l>
                     <l>If I had not been dead, I'd fain have ſeen,</l>
                     <l>Who durſt affront one of my haughty meen.</l>
                     <l>Sure he has wounded me, but I'm alive yet,</l>
                     <l>And pretty ſound; but moſt confounded wet.</l>
                     <l>I'll take advice to know where 'tis I bleed;</l>
                     <l>Ha are you there? here's one lies dead indeed.</l>
                     <l>Quite mortal dead: Well Fellow! go thy way,</l>
                     <l>I'd Rifle thee, but that I dare not ſtay —</l>
                     <l>Had'ſt thou been wiſe, but all have not the gift,</l>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>Exit</hi> Laraſco.</stage>
                     <l>'Tis pity he ſhou'd live, that has no ſhift.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Neighbour.</speaker>
                     <l>Yes Coxcomb! I can ſhift as well as you —</l>
                     <l>I think I am the ſweeter of the two.</l>
                     <l>Send me well home, I'll ne'r come here agin,</l>
                     <l>I think him wiſeſt that preſerves his Skin. <stage>Exit.</stage>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="scene">
                  <head>Scene 3.</head>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Enter</hi> Mingo <hi>alone.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mingo.</speaker>
                     <l>Where am I now!</l>
                     <l>But 'tis no wonder if I've loſt my way,</l>
                     <l>My Maſter bad me near the Temple ſtay;</l>
                     <l>A place I ſeldom ſeek; The <hi>Donna</hi>'s Road</l>
                     <l>To chooſe new Servants, and the neweſt Mode.</l>
                     <l>Where earthly Saints are pray'd to, thoſe above</l>
                     <l>Sometimes are call'd on, in Intrigues of Love.</l>
                     <l>Where pious <hi>Dons</hi> with zealous Wives conſpire,</l>
                     <l>To raiſe the fortunes of their Husbands higher.</l>
                     <l>I'th' Temple I was Chriſten'd, but my fear</l>
                     <l>Tells me! 'twill fall if I agen come there—</l>
                     <l>Hold, my Maſter!— <stage>
                           <hi>Enter</hi> Alonzo.</stage>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Alon.</speaker>
                     <p>What didſt thou find the place?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Min.</speaker>
                     <l>Yes Sir, and ſaw your Friend, but thus it was;</l>
                     <l>After my haſty ſteps had found the dore,</l>
                     <l>All that I met, Nights ſilent liv'ry wore.</l>
                     <pb n="12" facs="tcp:199207:11"/>
                     <l>A Servant led me, where I ſaw Deſpair,</l>
                     <l>Juſt like <hi>Don Feniſe,</hi> ſitting in a Chair.</l>
                     <l>Not that <hi>Don Feniſe,</hi> who did uſe to be</l>
                     <l>The life of Mirth, and all good Company.</l>
                     <l>Not he, whoſe Soul was free as boundleſs Air,</l>
                     <l>Whoſe very name could chaſe away Deſpair.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Alon.</speaker>
                     <p>Rack me not with theſe delayes!</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Min.</speaker>
                     <l>Sir I ſaw,</l>
                     <l>A form would make a frozen <hi>Tartar</hi> thaw,</l>
                     <l>And melt his rocky Heart th'rough weeping Eyes:</l>
                     <l>His heavy Head upon his Shoulder lies,</l>
                     <l>His croſſed Arms ſupported by his Breſt,</l>
                     <l>He had no motion, yet he had no reſt.</l>
                     <l>His buſie Eyes fix'd to the earth — in brief,</l>
                     <l>He was the lively ſhape of killing grief.</l>
                     <l>At laſt as if the Dream had had an end,</l>
                     <l>He cry'd, <hi>Alonzo!</hi> Where's my deareſt Friend?</l>
                     <l>Then did I your approach and meſſage tell,</l>
                     <l>That did his eager grief a while repel,</l>
                     <l>But Sorrow ſoon did repoſſeſs his Face;</l>
                     <l>As Currents ſtop'd, more ſwiftly end their Race.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Alon.</speaker>
                     <l>It is not ſure within the pow'r of Fate,</l>
                     <l>To cauſe thoſe Wonders which thou doſt relate.</l>
                     <l>His heart ne'r entertain'd the — boldeſt fear,</l>
                     <l>And how could baſe Deſpair find entrance there.</l>
                     <l>What ever cauſe ſuch ſtrange effects create,</l>
                     <l>I will avert, or help to bear his Fate.</l>
                     <l>True Friendſhip, like rich Diamonds, we mark,</l>
                     <l>Whoſe rayes are moſt reſplendant in the dark.</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Mingo!</hi> make haſte<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and ſum up thy account,</l>
                     <l>Thy meri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>s may to higher Service mount;</l>
                     <l>Yet I have alwayes us'd thee well —</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Min.</speaker>
                     <p>Moſt true —</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Alon.</speaker>
                     <l>And have I not been oft abus'd by you?</l>
                     <l>Your wild Debaucheries in ev'ry place,</l>
                     <l>Made me a mark of Scorn, and rude Diſgrace.</l>
                     <l>I need not number up your Faults again,</l>
                     <l>Yet I reſolv'd to bring thee back to <hi>Spain:</hi>
                     </l>
                     <pb n="13" facs="tcp:199207:11"/>
                     <l>Here I diſmiſs you Sir; but ere you goe, <stage>Kicks him, and gives him Money.</stage>
                     </l>
                     <l>I'll pay thee leſs, and more than I do owe.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Min.</speaker>
                     <p>Ah Sir! I am a Rogue, but pray forgive —</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Alon.</speaker>
                     <l>Forget your ſaucy Tricks, and Civil live,</l>
                     <l>Perhaps you may be mine, if you amend— <stage>
                           <hi>Exit</hi> Alonzo.</stage>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Min.</speaker>
                     <l>This Gold is dear — Well! go thy wayes old Friend!</l>
                     <l>Revenge ſink deep, torment my injur'd — breſt,</l>
                     <l>'Till on his Ruine I have built my reſt.</l>
                     <l>How, turn honeſt! turn Beggar, give me Gold:</l>
                     <l>I'll think on Honeſty when I grow old.</l>
                     <l>For feeble helpleſs Age it may be good,</l>
                     <l>'Tis but a dull diſeaſe in youthful blood.</l>
                     <l>Among the modiſh <hi>French</hi> 'tis plain diſgrace,</l>
                     <l>Some of our <hi>Signiors</hi> too come on apace;</l>
                     <l>When they take up, the Tradeſman muſt not wait,</l>
                     <l>But hears the News, and has the courteous Hat,</l>
                     <l>Talks handſom Senſe, is heard like a Divine;</l>
                     <l>Pray Miſtre! ſtay and take a Glaſs of Wine —</l>
                     <l>But when he Dunns, and Cringes like a Slave,</l>
                     <l>Dam'ee! what would this paltry Fellow have?</l>
                     <l>Now I'm for any thing, all wayes I'll tread,</l>
                     <l>To find the path that does to Miſchief lead<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     </l>
                     <l>Kick'd! and turn'd off! I am a Rogue I know,</l>
                     <l>But to my Maſter I was never ſo.</l>
                     <l>Caſhier'd! and quite thrown by! well <hi>Don</hi> take heed,</l>
                     <l>Ere all be done, thy heart or mine ſhall bleed. <stage>Exit.</stage>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="act">
               <head>ACT II.</head>
               <div n="1" type="scene">
                  <head>Scene 1.</head>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Enter</hi> Don Manuel <hi>and</hi> Tereſa <hi>in the ſtreet.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Man.</speaker>
                     <l>A Meer miſchievous Plot, without all doubt;</l>
                     <l>Would any come to force a Woman out?</l>
                     <l>He could not do it but by her conſent,</l>
                     <l>No! no! I'll ne'r believe her innocent.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ter.</speaker>
                     <p>Are you ſure 'twas <hi>Don Feniſe?</hi> Think agen —</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Man.</speaker>
                     <p>Poh! think; I know him from a Thouſand men.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <pb n="14" facs="tcp:199207:12"/>
                     <speaker>Ter.</speaker>
                     <p>You may miſtake.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Man.</speaker>
                     <l>Miſtake! — pray is it day if the Sun ſhine?</l>
                     <l>That Queſtion's leſs impertinent than thine.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Enter</hi> Mingo.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mingo.</speaker>
                     <l>I've rack'd my Brains, and yet no way can find</l>
                     <l>To act a cloſe Revenge, Miſchief be kind!</l>
                     <l>And help me at a pinch — <stage>Aſide.</stage>
                     </l>
                     <l>Oh this dull Head, this barren Scull of mine!</l>
                     <l>Will nothing come? no Project? no Deſign?</l>
                     <l>Ha! what are theſe? —</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Man.</speaker>
                     <p>Yes you are; fooliſh and impertinent—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ter.</speaker>
                     <l>Ingrateful Raſcal! I was not impertinent,</l>
                     <l>When I help'd thee to my Maſters wealth,</l>
                     <l>And to two pretty little Girls, without one ſtroke of thy</l>
                     <l>Own labour; Heaven knows, and I have found</l>
                     <l>To my ſorrow, it will be long enough before thou</l>
                     <l>Wilt ſee one little, little Child, of thy own getting.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Man.</speaker>
                     <l>No, nor thou wert not impertinent, when thou</l>
                     <l>Didſt moſt inhumanely murther honeſt <hi>Sanchez.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ter.</speaker>
                     <l>Out thou Villain! was it not for thy ſake?</l>
                     <l>Thy hands too were as deep in as mine,</l>
                     <l>Heaven knows I meant no harm.</l>
                     <l>Ingrateful! doſt upbraid me with my good will?</l>
                     <l>I'll be reveng'd though I dye for't —</l>
                     <l>Thy Cheats are Villanies I will confeſs,</l>
                     <l>Thy puniſhment, will make my pain ſeem leſs.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Man.</speaker>
                     <l>Poh! you take Jeſting ſo unkindly— You know</l>
                     <l>Honey that I love you, And if my life onely</l>
                     <l>Were to be loſt, it ſhould go rather than I</l>
                     <l>Would ſee thee troubl'd thus: But —</l>
                     <l>It grieves my heart to think of loſing thee.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ter.</speaker>
                     <p>Ay, ay, theſe are your old wheedling Tricks —</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Man.</speaker>
                     <l>One can't praiſe you for your Contrivance,</l>
                     <l>Or your Courage, but y'are ſo angry —</l>
                     <l>Pry'thee my Deareſt! forgive me — I love</l>
                     <l>The very ground you tread on, And had rather ſee</l>
                     <pb n="15" facs="tcp:199207:12"/>
                     <l>Thee than my own heart-blood —Come you ſhall be kind</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ter.</speaker>
                     <l>My poor dear Rogue! I will forgive thee!</l>
                     <l>I will be kind, don't trouble thy ſelf. <stage>She weeps, and kiſſes him.</stage>
                     </l>
                     <l>What ſhall we do about <hi>Don Feniſe</hi> Dear!</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Man.</speaker>
                     <l>That bus'neſs muſt not be diſputed here;</l>
                     <l>Let's haſten home, leaſt ſome obſerving Eye</l>
                     <l>Should ruine us, Nay pry'thee no Reply —</l>
                     <l>I'll ſerve thee Honey with my deareſt blood.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ter.</speaker>
                     <p>My dear, dear <hi>Don!</hi> I'll dye to do thee good.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Exit</hi> Tereſa.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Man.</speaker>
                     <l>I mean no leſs; in ev'ry fooliſh ſtrife,</l>
                     <l>She threatens me to take away my life;</l>
                     <l>When ſhe's diſpatch'd aſide, I ſhall be free</l>
                     <l>And then, my coy <hi>Alcinda!</hi> I'm for thee —</l>
                     <l>With more then common madneſs — he's poſſeſt,</l>
                     <l>That layes up ſecrets in a female Breſt. <stage>
                           <hi>Exit</hi> Manuel.</stage>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mingo.</speaker>
                     <l>Thanks! Satan thanks! —</l>
                     <l>Theſe bloody Murthers, Cheats, and Villanies,</l>
                     <l>And ſomething more that undiſcover'd lies,</l>
                     <l>Are Riddles very dark, and intricate;</l>
                     <l>Teach me the reſt, and I'll adore thee Fate!</l>
                     <l>What I've already heard, commands a ſhare</l>
                     <l>For ſecreſie, as great as their parts are:</l>
                     <l>But I am injur'd, ſince he's wicked grown,</l>
                     <l>For I reſolv'd to be a Rogue alone.</l>
                     <l>Some way their bus'neſs ſhall my own advance,</l>
                     <l>I'll follow them, and leave the reſt to chance.</l>
                     <l>At leaſt their Crimes will teach me to invent,</l>
                     <l>A Rogue in miſchief is in's Element. <stage>
                           <hi>Exit</hi> Mingo.</stage>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="scene">
                  <head>Scene 2.</head>
                  <stage>Don Manuel<hi>'s Houſe.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Enter</hi> Roſella, Alcinda, <hi>and</hi> Leonella.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Alc.</speaker>
                     <l>What Viſage wears my Fate? what have they done?</l>
                     <l>The noiſe was very loud, Is <hi>Feniſe</hi> gone?</l>
                     <pb n="16" facs="tcp:199207:13"/>
                     <l>Safely got off or no? Why don't you ſpeak?</l>
                     <l>Should he be kill'd, my ſullen heart would break.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Leon.</speaker>
                     <p>He's ſafely gone, but all I fear is known —</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Alc.</speaker>
                     <p>Sure I heard their Swords; had he no wounds?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Leon.</speaker>
                     <p>None —</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Alc.</speaker>
                     <p>Henceforth we never meet.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Roſel.</speaker>
                     <l>Did acts of Love,</l>
                     <l>I'th' Sphere of Juſtice as of Power move,</l>
                     <l>Aſharp repentance wou'd ſucceed your Fact;</l>
                     <l>And you would ſuffer what you late did Act.</l>
                     <l>Some worthleſs object, on your ſelf would throw</l>
                     <l>That cruel ſcorn, you did to <hi>Feniſe</hi> ſhow.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Alc.</speaker>
                     <l>Juſtice is blind, and grown ſo modiſh too,</l>
                     <l>Like other Females, bribes muſt make her do:</l>
                     <l>Sword, Self-intereſt and Paſſion ſwayes,</l>
                     <l>But Love and beauty ev'ry thing obeyes.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Roſel.</speaker>
                     <l>She runs the common fate of all our Sex,</l>
                     <l>Whom natures too imperious Law, ſubjects</l>
                     <l>To her great Maſter-peice, victorious man:</l>
                     <l>And you <hi>Alcinda!</hi> know, you'r beauty can</l>
                     <l>Command ſo large a pow'r ore any heart,</l>
                     <l>As will oppoſe <hi>Aſtraea's</hi> weaker part.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Alc.</speaker>
                     <l>Beauty, the Toy you talk of, I diſown:</l>
                     <l>To my dull ſenſe it ſtill had been unknown,</l>
                     <l>If to your ſelf I had a ſtranger been;</l>
                     <l>Where all thoſe charming Vanities are ſeen,</l>
                     <l>Thoſe rare <hi>Chymaera's,</hi> flatt'ring Poets place</l>
                     <l>In the deſcription of a beautious face;</l>
                     <l>Thoſe that want faith, the fair <hi>Roſella</hi> view;</l>
                     <l>All Lovers write is verify'd in you.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Roſel.</speaker>
                     <l>Each wandring glance you make, a heart your prize,</l>
                     <l>By the Magnetick Vertue of your Eyes;</l>
                     <l>The am'rous Gallants here their ſervice pay,</l>
                     <l>You are their Saint, and at your feet they pray.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Leon.</speaker>
                     <l>The longeſt day would ſeem a midnights dream,</l>
                     <l>While they continue on this pleaſing theam.</l>
                     <l>Is not one Minute to <hi>Don Feniſe</hi> due?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Roſel.</speaker>
                     <p>Once more I muſt that hopeleſs ſuit renew.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <pb n="17" facs="tcp:199207:13"/>
                     <speaker>Alc.</speaker>
                     <l>Deſiſt <hi>Roſella!</hi> from a Sute ſo vain —</l>
                     <l>The Earth may move, before we meet again.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Roſ.</speaker>
                     <p>So brave a choice your Reaſon may approve.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Alc.</speaker>
                     <p>Reaſon was ne'r the meſſenger of Love.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ros.</speaker>
                     <p>Think, think <hi>Alcinda!</hi> you may Love too late—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Alc.</speaker>
                     <p>My humor's fix'd above the pow'r of Fate.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Leon.</speaker>
                     <l>Madam!</l>
                     <l>My zeal to ſerve you, ſhews my troubl'd mind,</l>
                     <l>To ſee you flie the Bleſſings Heav'n deſign'd;</l>
                     <l>O! could you think the joyes, that do attend</l>
                     <l>A marry'd life, this humor ſoon would end.</l>
                     <l>Think what entrancing pleaſure 'tis, to hold</l>
                     <l>Your Lover in your arms, and ſweetly fold</l>
                     <l>With cloſe embraces, and more lovely Twines,</l>
                     <l>Than claſping Ivy, or the winding Vines.</l>
                     <l>This idle peeviſh thing call'd Modeſty,</l>
                     <l>Is Womans moſt invet'rate Enemy:</l>
                     <l>Lay it aſide, none but our ſelves are here,</l>
                     <l>Bluſhes are vain when none but Women hear.</l>
                     <l>Sleep with a Man! what joy the thought of't brings,</l>
                     <l>This is no World to refuſe good things.</l>
                     <l>There needs no words, Your Eyes ſpeak your intent,</l>
                     <l>A Womans ſilence ſhews her full conſent.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Alc.</speaker>
                     <l>Perpetual ſilence ſeize thee! I admire</l>
                     <l>What leprous <hi>Daemon</hi> does thy Soul in<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>pire.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Roſ.</speaker>
                     <l>Baſe! — I know not what to call her, ſure</l>
                     <l>Nature wants Definitions ſo impure. <stage>
                           <hi>Exeunt</hi> Alcinda <hi>and</hi> Roſella.</stage>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Leon.</speaker>
                     <l>Truth ſeldom is accepted when 'tis plain;</l>
                     <l>But hang't! I'll ſoon retrieve their love again.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Enter</hi> Don Manuel <hi>and</hi> Tereſa, <hi>and</hi> Mingo <hi>after, obſerving them.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ter.</speaker>
                     <l>If you conſent, we yet may loſe our Fears,</l>
                     <l>And with their Bodies, cloyſter up our Cares,</l>
                     <l>Send them to th' Nunnery, and let's pretend</l>
                     <l>Zeal to Religion is our onely end.</l>
                     <l>Let them drop Beads—</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Man.</speaker>
                     <p>From thence what can ariſe?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ter.</speaker>
                     <p>In their Concealment all our ſafety lies.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <pb n="18" facs="tcp:199207:14"/>
                     <speaker>Man.</speaker>
                     <p>Can that contribute ought to hide our Crimes?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ter.</speaker>
                     <l>Yes, very much theſe Superſtitious times;</l>
                     <l>'Twill gain their higheſt praiſe, who can depaint</l>
                     <l>Miſchief ſo fair, it may deceive a Saint.</l>
                     <l>In this quick-ſighted Age that we live in,</l>
                     <l>Religion is the ſafeſt Veil for Sin.</l>
                     <l>While they do breathe an unconfined Air,</l>
                     <l>Our Ruines imminent, Objects ſo fair</l>
                     <l>Endure the ſearch of many prying Eyes;</l>
                     <l>You know what Dangers may from thence ariſe.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Man.</speaker>
                     <p>I like thy counſel well — but —</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ter.</speaker>
                     <l>But! — but what?</l>
                     <l>Vengeance purſues us, yet his blood ſeems hot</l>
                     <l>An<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> reeking for Revenge, methinks I hear</l>
                     <l>The wind cry Murther in my guilty Ear —</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Man.</speaker>
                     <l>Dear Duck! enough, th'art wiſe; it ſhall be ſo —</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Roſella</hi> to the Nunnery ſhall go,</l>
                     <l>That will ſecure us, though <hi>Alcinda</hi> ſtay,</l>
                     <l>On her ſide there's no danger in delay.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ter.</speaker>
                     <l>Steal to your ruine; do! — let both be gone;</l>
                     <l>Why ſhould one go, or t'other ſtay alone?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Man.</speaker>
                     <l>Nay no great matter, but 'tis chargeable;</l>
                     <l>Truth is, I love <hi>Alcinda</hi> yet too well. <stage>Aſide.</stage>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ter.</speaker>
                     <l>What ſhould this mean? the charge will be but ſmall —</l>
                     <l>Better loſe part, than give account for all.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Man.</speaker>
                     <p>Let's in and think upon't —</p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Exeunt</hi> Manuel <hi>and</hi> Tereſa.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Leon.</speaker>
                     <l>What can this be?</l>
                     <l>Vengeance and Blood, this is too hard for me —</l>
                     <l>Some monſtrous miſchief, though 'tis cloſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> as Night,</l>
                     <l>Time will reveal it, That brings all to light.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Exit</hi> Leonella.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mingo,</speaker>
                     <l>Strange! above wonder ſtrange! and falls ſo right</l>
                     <l>As if the gods themſelves lov'd deeds of Night.</l>
                     <l>To bring me there, juſt at that minute too;</l>
                     <l>I'll talk no more, but ſtudy what to do.</l>
                     <l>In vain you ſtrive to prop your falling State,</l>
                     <l>Your Lives are mine, this Tongue commands your Fate.</l>
                     <pb n="19" facs="tcp:199207:14"/>
                     <l>Sure that was <hi>Leonilla</hi> ſtai'd behind —</l>
                     <l>My quondam Miſtriſs; I'll ſoon make her kind.</l>
                     <l>What ſights are here?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Enter</hi> Alcinda <hi>and</hi> Leonella, Roſella <hi>following them.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Alc.</speaker>
                     <p>Receive no anſwer, nor no meſſage hear.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Roſ.</speaker>
                     <l>Examine ore your heart, ſhe ſhall not go:</l>
                     <l>You too much malice with your power ſhow.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Alc.</speaker>
                     <l>Are you unkind? then who can be believ'd?</l>
                     <l>I had commanded had my Father liv'd.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Exit</hi> Alcinda <hi>weeping.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Roſ.</speaker>
                     <l>Go, ſerve her will, 'tis ſtrange, a gallant man</l>
                     <l>Should love ſo truly, and ſo long in vain;</l>
                     <l>Dearly I love him, yet I know not why,</l>
                     <l>I'm ne'r ſo happy as when he is nigh.</l>
                     <l>Yet, for a husband if I make my choice,</l>
                     <l>His Intereſt will never win my voice.</l>
                     <l>And yet I love him ſtill — ha! to what end?</l>
                     <l>Were it not virtuous I ſhould hate my friend;</l>
                     <l>Love is as yet a ſtranger in my breſt.</l>
                     <l>I will not like a Tyrant treat a gueſt:</l>
                     <l>Yet, to ſecure my heart from a ſurprize,</l>
                     <l>I'll ſet a guard of Virtue in my Eyes,</l>
                     <l>And while my Love to Virtue does ſubmit,</l>
                     <l>I will believe it fair, and welcome it.</l>
                     <l>And love him ſtill —</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Enter</hi> Alcinda.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Alc.</speaker>
                     <p>Will you my Rival grow?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Roſ.</speaker>
                     <p>Ne'r did a Siſter love a Brother ſo.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Alc.</speaker>
                     <l>You ſhall not love him, nor ſhall he love you,</l>
                     <l>His Vows have made him mine, ſure Vows are true.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Roſ.</speaker>
                     <l>You ſlight his Vows, his Courtſhip diſapprove;</l>
                     <l>This Jealouſie ſhews the exceſs of Love — <stage>Aſide.</stage>
                     </l>
                     <l>Becauſe You hate him muſt I do ſo too?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Alc.</speaker>
                     <l>Fool not your ſelf, I love him more than you:</l>
                     <pb n="20" facs="tcp:199207:15"/>
                     <l>You love! this News ſhall to your Father's ear —</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Roſ.</speaker>
                     <l>Pray Heav'n your flame does not too late appear;</l>
                     <l>On you <hi>Alcinda!</hi> he has fix'd his Love</l>
                     <l>Too conſtantly to ſuffer a Remove.</l>
                     <l>Diſperſe your jealous frowns, I have my end,</l>
                     <l>When He your Husband is, and you my friend.</l>
                     <l>May you enjoy him ſtill, and happy be,</l>
                     <l>Above the fears of Infelicity.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Alc.</speaker>
                     <l>Take him you, if you pleaſe, for I know none</l>
                     <l>So fond to dye for him — <stage>
                           <hi>Exit</hi> Alcinda.</stage>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Roſ.</speaker>
                     <l>So coyly gone?</l>
                     <l>What ſickly Fancies do this Maid poſſeſs?</l>
                     <l>She ſeems to hate, yet loves to an exceſs.</l>
                     <l>Ah <hi>Feniſe!</hi> from my heart I pity thee — <stage>
                           <hi>Exit</hi> Roſella.</stage>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mingo.</speaker>
                     <l>Both are exactly fair in ev'ry part;</l>
                     <l>A virtuous flame ſeems to aſſault my heart,</l>
                     <l>And prompts me to be good; bids me declare</l>
                     <l>All I have heard; But they are both too fair —</l>
                     <l>Ha! if things fall right, One may be my own;</l>
                     <l>So Innocent! — I dare not ſtay alone —</l>
                     <l>My better <hi>Genius</hi> tempts me to be juſt,</l>
                     <l>'Twill gain their Favours, and oblige their Truſt:</l>
                     <l>Death! I am ruin'd by a longer ſtay —</l>
                     <l>The Maid I'll follow now, ſhe went this way. <stage>
                           <hi>Exit</hi> Mingo.</stage>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="scene">
                  <head>Scene 3.</head>
                  <stage>Feniſe<hi>'s Houſe.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Enter</hi> Don Feniſe <hi>alone.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fen.</speaker>
                     <l>When giddy Fortune ceaſes to be coy,</l>
                     <l>The ſtorms we paſt, increaſe our preſent joy.</l>
                     <l>But when her various Front grows black again,</l>
                     <l>That very joy adds to ſucceeding pain.</l>
                     <l>This day I have convers'd with each extream,</l>
                     <l>Deſpair is fix'd, hope vaniſh'd like a dream.</l>
                     <l>Ah <hi>Alcinda!</hi> why ſhould I think on her,</l>
                     <l>On that ungrateful, cruel murtherer?</l>
                     <pb n="21" facs="tcp:199207:15"/>
                     <l>'Tis ſhe.</l>
                     <l>That values not my conſtancy, nor Me —</l>
                     <l>Diſpiſes all my Vows; yet could ſhe prove</l>
                     <l>More cruel than her ſelf, ſtill I muſt love.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Enter</hi> Laraſco <hi>fearfully, and ſhuts the dore after him.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fen.</speaker>
                     <p>What means this ſaucy haſte? what makes you run?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Lar.</speaker>
                     <l>O Sir! Sir! you are ruin'd! loſt! undone!</l>
                     <l>Fly Sir! fly, the,—O-O-Of—Off—Officer —</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fen.</speaker>
                     <l>What Officer? pry'thee ask leave of fear</l>
                     <l>To tell the Cauſe —</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Lar.</speaker>
                     <l>Oh Sir! they are at the dore —</l>
                     <l>That I had been but fairly kill'd before!</l>
                     <l>Now we ſhall be Hang'd; both, both Hang'd, I know't,</l>
                     <l>Methinks I feel the Slip about my Throat —</l>
                     <l>Good honeſt <hi>Dun!</hi> don't ſtrain the Rope ſo hard —</l>
                     <l>O let a little time to pray be ſpar'd! —</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fen.</speaker>
                     <p>Villain! what ayles the fellow? —</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Lar.</speaker>
                     <l>Dear Chriſtian friends!</l>
                     <l>If you'll avoid ſuch baſe, ſuch ſhameful ends,</l>
                     <l>Beware of Wenching, and Ill company;</l>
                     <l>Wenching! 'tis Wenching brings me here to dye.</l>
                     <l>Curſe on ſuch folly—pry'thee let me pray;</l>
                     <l>One little minute! — Oh! he drives away —</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fen.</speaker>
                     <l>Nay if y'are going take my bleſſing too —</l>
                     <l>This fear has made him mad; what wouldſt thou do</l>
                     <l>Speak! where haſt thou been! —</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Lar.</speaker>
                     <l>Mercy good my Lord!</l>
                     <l>I ne'r had Courage to behold a Sword.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fen.</speaker>
                     <p>Recall your ſenſe, and tell me what you mean.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Lar.</speaker>
                     <l>Ah Sir! I ne'r ſhall have my Senſe agen.</l>
                     <l>The dreadfull roaring Officers, without</l>
                     <l>Are ſent to ſeize you, Look you all about.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fen.</speaker>
                     <p>To ſeize me! for what? —</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Lar.</speaker>
                     <l>They'l tell you if you ſtay —</l>
                     <l>Have you forgot the Man you kill'd to day?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <pb n="22" facs="tcp:199207:16"/>
                     <speaker>Fen.</speaker>
                     <p>Is the man dead? —</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Lar.</speaker>
                     <l>I! I! Sir! dead's a ſtone —</l>
                     <l>A happy, happy man, his Cares are done.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Exeunt</hi> Feniſe <hi>and</hi> Laraſco.</stage>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Enter</hi> Alonzo.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Alon.</speaker>
                     <l>What am I like, the Servants fly me ſo?</l>
                     <l>I am reſolv'd to find him e'r I go —</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Don Feniſe! Don Feniſe!</hi> 
                        <stage>
                           <hi>Exit</hi> Alonzo.</stage>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Enter</hi> Feniſe <hi>and</hi> Laraſco.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Lar.</speaker>
                     <l>Hark how they Roar! —</l>
                     <l>Pray Sir be gone before they force the dore.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fen.</speaker>
                     <l>Raſcal! go you, tell the Officious ſlaves,</l>
                     <l>Thoſe that do enter here, do ſeek their graves.</l>
                     <l>I never fear'd thee death! thy fierceſt brow</l>
                     <l>Cou'd ne'r diſturb me; but th'art lovely now.</l>
                     <l>With greedy armes, ſuch as glad Bridegrooms wear,</l>
                     <l>When full enjoyments drown their wooing fear,</l>
                     <l>I'll meet my Deſtiny, and hug my fate: <stage>Feniſe. <hi>draws.</hi>
                        </stage>
                     </l>
                     <l>To end our Cares death alwayes comes too late.</l>
                     <l>Now will her ſcorn, now will my Love have end —</l>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>A noiſe within,</hi> Alonzo <hi>forces the dore, and enters with his Sword drawn.</hi>
                     </stage>
                     <l>Here here's <hi>Feniſe!</hi>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Alon.</speaker>
                     <p>Is't thus you meet your Friend?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fen.</speaker>
                     <l>With my <hi>Alonzo,</hi> thus I will contend.</l>
                     <l>Fate I deſpiſe, and Love I will forget;</l>
                     <l>In ſpight of both I may be happy yet.</l>
                     <l>Welcome dear Friend! —</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Alon.</speaker>
                     <l>But can my <hi>Feniſe</hi> be</l>
                     <l>Still conſtant to that friendſhip vow'd to me?</l>
                     <l>Has not ſome nobler Object ſtole that part,</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Alonzo</hi> once poſſeſt in <hi>Feniſe</hi> heart?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fen.</speaker>
                     <l>No more of this; <hi>Alonzo</hi> wrongs me much,</l>
                     <l>To think my Vows, or friendſhip can be ſuch.</l>
                     <pb n="23" facs="tcp:199207:16"/>
                     <l>But I may juſtly think your kindneſs loſt,</l>
                     <l>That would not let me meet you on the Coaſt.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Alon.</speaker>
                     <l>I ſuffer'd ſtricter penance than was due,</l>
                     <l>For that which injur'd me much more than you.</l>
                     <l>When tedious abſence had endear'd your ſight,</l>
                     <l>And rais'd Impatience to the utmoſt height:</l>
                     <l>Yet then, then did I for admittance wait;</l>
                     <l>And now, you chide me 'cauſe I come ſo late.</l>
                     <l>When ſpight of Locks and Dores I made my way,</l>
                     <l>You interpos'd your Sword to make me ſtay.</l>
                     <l>I thought it ſome Inchanted Houſe; for here</l>
                     <l>One Servant flies, another hides him there:</l>
                     <l>Scarce could I reach one with my doubting eyes,</l>
                     <l>But like ſome falſe deluding ſhade he flies;</l>
                     <l>At laſt I turn'd, and ſaw the armed Rout</l>
                     <l>Begin to march —</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Lar.</speaker>
                     <p>'Twas time to look about.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fen.</speaker>
                     <l>This way I made, how I got off you ſaw;</l>
                     <l>Unveil theſe Myſteries, what made you draw?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Alon.</speaker>
                     <l>Come Sir! I will inform you all within;</l>
                     <l>Diſcourſe ſo ſad, will ſoon enough begin.</l>
                     <l>Oh my <hi>Alonzo!</hi> That my whole Eſtate</l>
                     <l>Could call this Morning back; but 'tis too late.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Exeunt</hi> Feniſe, Alonzo <hi>and</hi> Laraſco.</stage>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Enter</hi> Mingo <hi>and</hi> Leonella <hi>in the Street.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Min.</speaker>
                     <l>My Dear! this very Morning did my feet</l>
                     <l>Salute this ground; where all my wiſhes meet,</l>
                     <l>Finding my lovely <hi>Leonella</hi> here:</l>
                     <l>More beautiful than when I laſt did ſee her —</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Leon.</speaker>
                     <p>Your old diſſembling Tricks —</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Min.</speaker>
                     <l>By th' light I ſee,</l>
                     <l>My love is dead to all the World, but thee.</l>
                     <l>Had ſpiteful Death extinguiſh'd thy dear light,</l>
                     <l>I had purſu'd thee to eternal Night.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Leon.</speaker>
                     <p>O fie on you men! for y'are all falſe —</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <pb n="24" facs="tcp:199207:17"/>
                     <speaker>Min.</speaker>
                     <l>Look here, though men are falſe, Angels are true.</l>
                     <stage>Gives her Mony.</stage>
                     <l>Theſe, and ſome hundreds more are kept for you;</l>
                     <l>Pry'thee be mollify'd, Love made me trace</l>
                     <l>Ten thouſand miles, to ſee thy pretty face.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Leon.</speaker>
                     <p>Since here we parted not, this can't be true.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Min.</speaker>
                     <l>That you liv'd, by meer inſtinct I knew;</l>
                     <l>Divided wormes their parts will reunite,</l>
                     <l>Although the loving creatures have no ſight.</l>
                     <l>But Nature did in me much ſtronger prove,</l>
                     <l>Aſſiſted by my reaſon, and my Love.</l>
                     <l>Within thy breaſt I left my better part,</l>
                     <l>And now my body comes to find my heart.</l>
                     <l>Speak my dear Oracle! pronounce my Fate!</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Leon.</speaker>
                     <p>Well, I'll conſider on't —</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Min.</speaker>
                     <l>Where ſhall I wait</l>
                     <l>To hear my Sentence? I'll attend thee home —</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Leon.</speaker>
                     <l>O by no means; You muſt not thither come:</l>
                     <l>Our Houſe to Men will no admittance give.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Min.</speaker>
                     <p>See thee I muſt, or elſe I cannot live —</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Leon.</speaker>
                     <l>A Small diſturbance we this morning made,</l>
                     <l>Has made my Maſter jealous of his ſhade.</l>
                     <l>Man, and Male-kind ſo mortally he hates,</l>
                     <l>His Malice doth extend to Dogs and Cats:</l>
                     <l>My Ladies Lapdog, and the Cat were found</l>
                     <l>Contriving of a Rape, and both were drown'd.</l>
                     <l>A Maſſacre's deſign'd againſt the Mice—</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Min.</speaker>
                     <p>No way to cheat this Tyrant? — no device!</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Leon.</speaker>
                     <l>No; — Yes there is, if you can counterfeit</l>
                     <l>An Eunuch handſomely, 'twill do the feat.</l>
                     <l>For ſome ſuch property he'll entertain,</l>
                     <l>To guard his dore; leſt men ſhould come again—</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Min.</speaker>
                     <l>An Eunuch! all your Sex will loath my ſight,</l>
                     <l>More than She-Papiſts do a <hi>Lenten</hi> night.</l>
                     <l>And treat me, as the angry <hi>Welchmen</hi> prey</l>
                     <l>On Puppets, that affront Saint <hi>David</hi>'s day:</l>
                     <l>Yet, I'll about it ſtrait, that thou may'ſt ſee,</l>
                     <l>I dare do any thing to purchaſe thee.</l>
                     <pb n="25" facs="tcp:199207:17"/>
                     <l>Lend me one kiſs, nay fie! hold up thy head:</l>
                     <l>I'll pay thee Intereſt when we meet a Bed. <stage>
                           <hi>Exit</hi> Mingo.</stage>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Leon.</speaker>
                     <l>Fie! fie! I hate you now — I muſt be coy,</l>
                     <l>Though he's ſharp ſet, too eaſie Love will cloy:</l>
                     <l>Men are ſo Femaliz'd, ſo idle grown,</l>
                     <l>They court the Coy, and ſlight what may be won.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Exit</hi> Leonella.</stage>
               </div>
               <trailer>The End of the Second Act.</trailer>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="act">
               <head>ACT III.</head>
               <div n="1" type="scene">
                  <head>Scene 1.</head>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Enter</hi> Laraſco <hi>alone in</hi> Fenis<hi>'s Houſe.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Lar.</speaker>
                     <l>MAlicious Rogues lie cloſe, lurk any where;</l>
                     <l>Men may be kill'd, yet ſee no danger near.</l>
                     <l>Would all like wiſer Schoolmen fight with words,</l>
                     <l>I could be Valiant; but I hate theſe Swords —</l>
                     <l>I can eat like a Lyon; and for Drink,</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Bacchus</hi> himſelf ſhould never make me ſhrink.</l>
                     <l>Theſe are rare parts, the Virtues in requeſt,</l>
                     <l>What pity 'tis I cannot reach the reſt?</l>
                     <l>O had I but the heart, to thunder out</l>
                     <l>A Roaring Oath, look big, and ſtare about:</l>
                     <l>Cry Damm'ee! with a Grace; then ſtamp, and frown,</l>
                     <l>I were the moſt accompliſh'd Blade in Town.</l>
                     <l>(A ſilent Noiſe methinks invades my Ear)</l>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>Enter</hi> Leonella.</stage>
                     <l>Old Tormenter! I'll be reveng'd on her—</l>
                     <l>Dreadful <hi>Toledo!</hi> forth, thou truſty Blade,</l>
                     <l>That o're the Head and Ears in blood canſt wade.</l>
                     <l>Come out! here's food to fill thy hungry Maw —</l>
                     <l>I'll kill thee Villain! if thou wilt not draw.</l>
                     <l>Draw thou Son of a Whore!</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Leon.</speaker>
                     <p>Good <hi>Signior</hi> hold!</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Lar.</speaker>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Signior</hi> thy Siſter, thou paltry ſneaking Scold —</l>
                     <pb n="26" facs="tcp:199207:18"/>
                     <l>O I could ſwinge you now, I tell you that —</l>
                     <l>Wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>t now you Sir? ha! what would you be at?</l>
                     <l>Coward! I could eat thee —</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Leon.</speaker>
                     <l>Brave Sir! you fight</l>
                     <l>Prodigiouſly, and kill as oft as ſmite.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Lar.</speaker>
                     <p>Mortal! Thou ſay'ſt the Truth, come buſs me now —</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Leon.</speaker>
                     <l>Stay Sir! You hold your Sword I know not how,</l>
                     <l>I could inſtruct you in a better way.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Lar.</speaker>
                     <p>Do't; I command thee — <stage>He gives her his Sword.</stage>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Leon.</speaker>
                     <l>Then I muſt obey —</l>
                     <l>Raſcal! I'll teach you how to fight, I will, <stage>She beats him.</stage>
                     </l>
                     <l>Draw on your Friends? Sirrah I charge you kneel.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Lar.</speaker>
                     <p>Ah Madam Captain! my firſt Fault forgive —</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Leon.</speaker>
                     <l>Ne'r draw <hi>Toledo</hi> more as long's you live:</l>
                     <l>Next, I command thee that thou never fight,</l>
                     <l>But with our Sex —</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Lar.</speaker>
                     <p>That too ſhall be at Night.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Leon.</speaker>
                     <p>Leſt you are kick'd to Men give no affront;</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Lar.</speaker>
                     <p>Ah! you are merciful! indeed I wo'nt.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Leon.</speaker>
                     <p>Thy word ſhall ſerve — <stage>Gives him his Sword.</stage>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Lar.</speaker>
                     <l>Your Wars I'd fain be at —</l>
                     <l>I know already how to manage that.</l>
                     <l>Vollies of ſighs muſt firſt approach the Town,</l>
                     <l>To clear the brow of the defendant frown;</l>
                     <l>Kiſſes for Cannons, but my ſhot ſhould fall</l>
                     <l>Thicker than cannon bullets 'gainſt your Wall.</l>
                     <l>The ſturdy batt'ring Ram ſhould charge her home,</l>
                     <l>While her faint No's-ſupply the abſent drum.</l>
                     <l>The breach once made, e'r I attacque the fort,</l>
                     <l>I would diſmantl't, and peruſe my ſport:</l>
                     <l>And, if no modeiſh fireworks do remain,</l>
                     <l>I'll pitch my ſtandard, and fall on again —</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Leon.</speaker>
                     <l>But ſtay raſh Sir! ſuppoſe that you are beat,</l>
                     <l>A right ſtout man takes care for a retreat —</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Lar.</speaker>
                     <l>For a retreat? O prythee name it not —</l>
                     <l>I will o'recome; — Or periſh on the ſpot.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Leon.</speaker>
                     <p>Poh! where's your Maſter? ceaſe this idle Talk.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Lar.</speaker>
                     <l>He's muſing in his melancholly walk:</l>
                     <pb n="27" facs="tcp:199207:18"/>
                     <l>Let's to the Pantry firſt, for ſome relief;</l>
                     <l>There's heavenly Wine, and mighty glorious Beef.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Leon.</speaker>
                     <p>Thy heart lies in thy guts, Sirrah march on —</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Lar.</speaker>
                     <l>Love is a Diſh I cannot live upon;</l>
                     <l>Like my <hi>Camelion</hi> Maſter feed on looks,</l>
                     <l>If e'r I do, my guts will curſe the Cooks.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Exeunt</hi> Laraſco <hi>and</hi> Leonella.</stage>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="scene">
                  <head>Scene 2.</head>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Enter</hi> Don Feniſe <hi>and</hi> Don Alonzo <hi>in a Garden.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fen.</speaker>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Haſt thou ne'r ſeen a ſtately well rig'd Ship,</l>
                        <l>Charge through the foaming billows of the deep?</l>
                        <l>Whoſe batter'd Fabrick, ſtormy <hi>Neptune</hi> drawes</l>
                        <l>Into the ruines of his frothy Jawes;</l>
                        <l>Then ſhoots him up aloft, ſwift as a ſpear,</l>
                        <l>Sent to affront th' Olimpick Thunderer:</l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Jove</hi> loudly ſpeaks his ſcorn of <hi>Neptunes</hi> brave,</l>
                        <l>And lights the ſhip back to his watry grave.</l>
                        <l>From ev'ry point rough winds each other call,</l>
                        <l>Haſting to ſhare the glory of his fall:</l>
                        <l>The Veſſell ſtill bears up, though thus oppreſt,</l>
                        <l>The Wind grown weary, gives the water reſt;</l>
                        <l>The skies ſerene, and all the ſtorm blown ore,</l>
                        <l>The longing Veſſel makes the wiſh'd for ſhore;</l>
                        <l>When, on a lurking Rock, ſo near the coaſt,</l>
                        <l>She ſplits; and juſt i'th' harbour all is loſt.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>So Fortune plaid with me, I triumph'd ore</l>
                        <l>The ſtorms of her diſdain, had ſight of ſhore;</l>
                        <l>That happy port of which my Love did ſteer,</l>
                        <l>If Earth has yet a paradiſe, 'tis there —</l>
                        <l>But now <hi>Alonzo!</hi> —</l>
                        <l>Mark the decree of my too cruel fate,</l>
                        <l>Juſt on th' arrival of this glorious ſtate,</l>
                        <l>Ev'n in the proſpect of my utmoſt joyes,</l>
                        <l>It ſhipwracks all my bliſs, my hope deſtroyes.</l>
                        <pb n="28" facs="tcp:199207:19"/>
                        <l>Which now lyes ſunck in th' Ocean of deſpair;</l>
                        <l>Sunck! for ever ſunck! —</l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Alon.</speaker>
                     <l>Time may repair</l>
                     <l>Thy heavy loſs, and raiſe thy drooping fate.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fen.</speaker>
                     <p>Never! —</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Alon.</speaker>
                     <l>This paſſion's too effeminate;</l>
                     <l>A helpleſs Woman can, like thee, depaint</l>
                     <l>Impatient ſorrow in a weak complaint;</l>
                     <l>Rayl on Siniſter ſtars, and execrate</l>
                     <l>The dire effects of her miſguided fate.</l>
                     <l>Such paſſive Soules teach fate to tyrannize.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fen.</speaker>
                     <p>What is't your active ſpirit would adviſe?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Alon.</speaker>
                     <l>Deſpiſe thy miſtriſs, and thy Rival kill;</l>
                     <l>This way to doat will be excuſeable.</l>
                     <l>Do but the difference of paſſions prove,</l>
                     <l>You'l find revenge is ſweeter far then Love.</l>
                     <l>Thy more ſucceſsful Rival muſt be ſlain —</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fen.</speaker>
                     <p>I have no Rival, but her juſt diſdain.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Alon.</speaker>
                     <p>If it be juſt, you ought not to complain.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fen.</speaker>
                     <l>Were it not ſo my caſe were not ſo ſad,</l>
                     <l>Then hope might live; and pity might be had.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Alon.</speaker>
                     <l>If not to thee, where will ſhe give her heart?</l>
                     <l>The ſun ne'r ſaw a man of more deſert.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fen.</speaker>
                     <l>Should thrifty nature ſpend her precious ſtore.</l>
                     <l>T'enrich one Heroe, 'till her ſelf grow poor;</l>
                     <l>She has not worth enough to buy the priſe</l>
                     <l>Of one rich ſmile, from her reſiſtleſs Eyes.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Alon.</speaker>
                     <l>A gallant Woman! were theſe fancies true:</l>
                     <l>But as ſhe's fair, ſo ſhe is Cruel too.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fen.</speaker>
                     <p>There I'm loſt —</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Alon.</speaker>
                     <l>Yes, to any thing of man,</l>
                     <l>Or reaſon thou art loſt; recal again</l>
                     <l>That royal Exile; where wild paſſions ſway,</l>
                     <l>The Empire of the Soul will ſoon decay.</l>
                     <l>So Ships without a knowing Guide are toſs'd,</l>
                     <l>By ev'ry Guſt in danger to be loſt.</l>
                     <l>Diſtraction in thy fancy needs muſt raign,</l>
                     <l>Since it is form'd by a diſtracted Brain.</l>
                     <pb n="29" facs="tcp:199207:19"/>
                     <l>Reaſon would tell thee, Nature did deſign</l>
                     <l>The female ſex ſlaves to the Maſculine;</l>
                     <l>'Till we are pleas'd to take them into grace,</l>
                     <l>And bring the rib back to its proper place.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fen.</speaker>
                     <l>But love, the King of paſſions, wont allow,</l>
                     <l>His ſubjects ſhould to reaſons Scepter bow.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Alon.</speaker>
                     <l>Unreaſonable love is Luſt; a beaſt</l>
                     <l>May with a brutiſh paſſion be poſſeſt.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fen.</speaker>
                     <l>You ſay you never lov'd, then how can you</l>
                     <l>Define a paſſion which you never knew?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Alon.</speaker>
                     <lg>
                        <l>I love good horſes, ſport on ſprightly Wine;</l>
                        <l>This reaſon does allow, there's none for thine.</l>
                        <l>If thou lov'ſt Beauty, view the forward ſpring:</l>
                        <l>Seek it in Books if Virtue be the thing.</l>
                        <l>Canſt thou with ladders ſcale the ſtarry grove,</l>
                        <l>And mount the aery battlements of <hi>Jove?</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>That, and much more thou ſooner may'ſt fulfil,</l>
                        <l>Then court a froward Woman from her Will.</l>
                        <l>She makes thy ſighs and miſeries her ſport,</l>
                        <l>Thou, like a fawning Span'el lov'ſt her for't.</l>
                        <l>How vain, how fooliſh? how ridiculous?</l>
                        <l>Poor and contemptible this paſſion ſhows?</l>
                        <l>All for a Woman too; a falſe delight,</l>
                        <l>Firſt fram'd by Natures drowzy overſight:</l>
                        <l>Begot by giddy drunkards, whoſe ſick braines</l>
                        <l>And reeling thoughts, their riper Age explaines.</l>
                        <l>A painted nothing, gaudy butterfly;</l>
                        <l>Black at the heart, though pleaſing to the Eye.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>This is thy Goddeſs, Miſtriſs of thy Fate,</l>
                        <l>Henceforth we will perſue them with a hate</l>
                        <l>As great as was thy Love, and thou and I</l>
                        <l>Will from their charmes, as from diſeaſes fly.</l>
                        <l>Summon thy exil'd reaſon to her throne.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fen.</speaker>
                     <l>Your witty malice you in vain have ſhown;</l>
                     <l>Your counſel is a ſenſeleſs dream to me,</l>
                     <l>Love knows no reaſon, no Philoſophy.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Alon.</speaker>
                     <l>Your ruine faces you, yet you run on</l>
                     <l>Like loſeing Gamſters, ev'n when hope is gon.</l>
                     <pb n="30" facs="tcp:199207:20"/>
                     <l>True friends no cloſe diſtinction make, one fate</l>
                     <l>In joy and grief they both participate.</l>
                     <l>But I am troubleſome, unwelcome grown,</l>
                     <l>You will be happy when you are alone — <stage>Going out.</stage>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fen.</speaker>
                     <l>Stay! ſtay <hi>Alonzo.</hi> pr'ythee pardon me;</l>
                     <l>To pettiſh age, or young ſimplicity</l>
                     <l>We more allow — Loves dotage I confeſs,</l>
                     <l>But have not power yet to make it leſs.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Enter</hi> Leonella <hi>with a Letter.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Leon.</speaker>
                     <l>O my goodneſs! what a ſweet man is here?</l>
                     <l>A lovely tempting ſhape! — <stage>
                           <hi>She gives the Letter to</hi> Feniſe.</stage>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fen.</speaker>
                     <l>Is it from her?</l>
                     <l>Thou bringſt a bleſſing in each Character.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Alon.</speaker>
                     <l>What's the decree? does ſhe propoſe a peace?</l>
                     <l>Thy looks are ſad, pry'thee explain the caſe.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fen.</speaker>
                     <p>Read there —</p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Alonzo</hi> reads the Letter.</stage>
                  <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
                     <body>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Alon.</speaker>
                           <l>The firſt part of my promiſe being paſt,</l>
                           <l>You must aſſist me to perform the last.</l>
                           <l>When I did yield to go, you did agree,</l>
                           <l>This day orepast I ſhould be ever free<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                           </l>
                           <l>That done, which Gratitude oblig'd me to,</l>
                           <l>I'll to my ſelf be just, as well's to you.</l>
                           <l>You must forget me, never ſee me more:</l>
                           <l>'Tis fit you keep, what you ſo freely ſwore.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <closer>
                           <signed>Alcinda.</signed>
                        </closer>
                     </body>
                  </floatingText>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Alon.</speaker>
                     <l>Before we number many flying houres,</l>
                     <l>This bluſtring March ſhall melt in <hi>April</hi> ſhowres.</l>
                     <l>Hear me — <stage>Feniſe <hi>and</hi> Alonzo <hi>whiſper.</hi>
                        </stage>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Leon.</speaker>
                     <l>Oh that I were a Lady for his ſake!</l>
                     <l>A man made up in wax —</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Alon.</speaker>
                     <l>How Sir not take?</l>
                     <pb n="31" facs="tcp:199207:20"/>
                     <l>Then I doat too; come, worſe it cannot be;</l>
                     <l>Laugh heartily, and leave the reſt to me.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fen.</speaker>
                     <p>O I cannot —</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Alon.</speaker>
                     <l>What will you ſtill be mad?</l>
                     <l>You cannot win her by your looking ſad.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fen.</speaker>
                     <p>Well, I ſubmit, but if your project fail —</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Alon.</speaker>
                     <p>Aſſure thy ſelf that nothing can prevail.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fen.</speaker>
                     <l>Never ſee me more! — ha ha he!</l>
                     <l>How imperiouſly theſe Ladies write?</l>
                     <l>Muſt forget me! — ha ha he!</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Alon.</speaker>
                     <l>Bravely done, by this light.</l>
                     <l>Yet leaves thy choice as free as heretofore,</l>
                     <l>'Tis fit you keep what you ſo freely ſwore.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fen.</speaker>
                     <l>Go tell the Toy you came from, I'm above</l>
                     <l>The power of her malice or her love.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Leon.</speaker>
                     <l>Alack alack good Gentleman! theſe fits</l>
                     <l>Of Love, have put him quite beſide his wits.</l>
                     <l>He is become inſenſible of's pain.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fen.</speaker>
                     <lg>
                        <l>O No! my ſenſe is juſt return'd again —</l>
                        <l>Thy Lady <hi>Circe</hi>'s charming ſpells are broke,</l>
                        <l>And now I'm free'd from her inchanting Yoke.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>As one, that's by an <hi>Ignis fatuus</hi> led</l>
                        <l>To ſome aſpiring Rock, whoſe craggy head,</l>
                        <l>Hangs drooping ore the deep unmeaſur'd Main,</l>
                        <l>Flyes with amazed horrour back again;</l>
                        <l>So I, miſled by thoſe falſe lights her Eyes,</l>
                        <l>Was like to fall loves fooliſh Sacrifice;</l>
                        <l>But now my Soul ſee's clear, I'll doat no more,</l>
                        <l>But fly thoſe dangers I purſu'd before.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Leon.</speaker>
                     <l>If I return this meſſage Sir! I'll add</l>
                     <l>That when you ſpoke it, you were raving mad.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fen.</speaker>
                     <l>Woman! I'm calm and ſerious, ſay from me</l>
                     <l>That light and darkneſs ſooner may agree,</l>
                     <l>Than we two meet — Oh what do I intend!</l>
                     <l>I ſhall undo my ſelf to pleaſe my friend.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Alon.</speaker>
                     <l>No flinching now, I'll warrant thee ſhe's thine.</l>
                     <l>Read her Note agen.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fen.</speaker>
                     <l>This is very fine! <stage>Reads.</stage>
                     </l>
                     <pb n="32" facs="tcp:199207:21"/>
                     <l>Pray let no more enticeing Notes be brought,</l>
                     <l>'Tis loſs of time to read her idle thought.</l>
                     <l>Yet, this I will preſerve, as ſlaves made free</l>
                     <l>Keep that which juſtifies their libertie.</l>
                     <l>Oh <hi>Alonzo!</hi> —</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Alon.</speaker>
                     <l>No more, 'tis bravely done.</l>
                     <l>March off — I'll finiſh what's ſo well begun <stage>
                           <hi>Exit</hi> Feuiſe.</stage>
                     </l>
                     <l>Go tell your fooliſh Lady how you ſped,</l>
                     <l>Her ſnare is broken, and the Bird is fled — <stage>
                           <hi>Exit</hi> Leonella.</stage>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Enter</hi> Don Feniſe.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fen.</speaker>
                     <l>One ſcorching glance, If from her eyes it came,</l>
                     <l>Would ſet a frozen <hi>Scythian</hi> in a flame.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Alon.</speaker>
                     <l>How's this? relaps'd agen! can you be free,</l>
                     <l>Yet hug thoſe Chains that cauſe your miſerie?</l>
                     <l>Y'are like a poor Idolater, betray'd</l>
                     <l>To ſerve that Idol which your ſelf have made.</l>
                     <l>Think all are beauitful, and 'twill appear,</l>
                     <l>You love your own fond fancy more then her.</l>
                     <l>You may as ſoon forget her if you pleaſe —</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fen.</speaker>
                     <l>Fancy can be no cure for Loves diſeaſe:</l>
                     <l>We cannot of our ſelves, or love, or hate,</l>
                     <l>Love ſhoots his golden Arrows ſure as fate,</l>
                     <l>Why do I talk! — I may as ſoon declare</l>
                     <l>To one born blind, what light and colours are.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Alon.</speaker>
                     <l>If y'are ſo fix'd, you will not be remov'd,</l>
                     <l>Leave nought untry'd to make your ſelf belov'd.</l>
                     <l>And, as you hope your wiſhes think on this,</l>
                     <l>Don't cringe and Idolize her for a kiſs,</l>
                     <l>But raviſh't from her lips, for to entreat</l>
                     <l>Makes her averſion ſeemingly more great;</l>
                     <l>A careleſs confidence makes Women yeild.</l>
                     <l>Thus you'l win honour, though you loſe the field.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fen.</speaker>
                     <l>Her conſtant virtue, ſeats her heart above</l>
                     <l>The mad attempts you uſe in looſer love.</l>
                     <l>Nor muſt we try thoſe idle wayes, to gain</l>
                     <l>A Sovereigns ſmiles, that do ore others raign.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <pb n="33" facs="tcp:199207:21"/>
                     <speaker>Alon.</speaker>
                     <l>A Sovereign! why you diſown'd her pow'r,</l>
                     <l>In ſending back her dear Embaſſadour</l>
                     <l>With ſo much ſcorn, as ſhew'd leſs love then hate.</l>
                     <l>Princes with ſlaves will ne'r capitulate.</l>
                     <l>Think you to win her now? be not ſo vain —</l>
                     <l>You vow'd a paſſion, and forſwor't again;</l>
                     <l>If, all your love and Courtſhip would not do,</l>
                     <l>Now y'are a Rebel 'tis in vain to wooe.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fen.</speaker>
                     <l>Treacherous man! was this thy policy?</l>
                     <l>Think'ſt thou to grow, where th'aſt ſupplanted me.</l>
                     <l>So bravely to betray me — ye juſt pow'rs!</l>
                     <l>'Tis not my own revenge I act but yours,</l>
                     <l>Direct my trembling Arme, teach it an art</l>
                     <l>To ſearch the ſecret paſſages of's heart —</l>
                     <l>Did troops of Devils guard thy perjur'd breſt,</l>
                     <l>(As ſure they do) for wert thou not poſſeſs't</l>
                     <l>With helliſh hopes, thou couldſt not be ſo baſe)</l>
                     <l>Thus would I ruin their abiding place.</l>
                     <l>Defend thy ſelf —</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Alon.</speaker>
                     <l>Dear <hi>Feniſe!</hi> hear me, if my blood may give</l>
                     <l>Eaſe to thy paſſion, I'll not wiſh to live:</l>
                     <l>Strike boldly here, and kill thy trueſt friend.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fen.</speaker>
                     <l>Think'ſt thou, this poor evaſion ſhall defend</l>
                     <l>Thy life? 'Thas rais'd my rage to ſuch a height,</l>
                     <l>That now I'll kill thee though thou wilt not fight.</l>
                     <l>Traytor to friendſhips and to honours law!</l>
                     <l>Coward! <hi>Alonzo's</hi> a Coward! now draw —</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Alon.</speaker>
                     <l>Your ſtrange diſtemper does my pity raiſe,</l>
                     <l>But not my anger —</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fen.</speaker>
                     <l>Ha! what is't he ſays?</l>
                     <l>His pity! Heav'ns his pity! that word</l>
                     <l>Wounds me more ſenſibly then can thy ſword.</l>
                     <l>Draw! or I'll murther thee, by Heav'n I will!</l>
                     <l>Though Angells guard thy life —</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Alon.</speaker>
                     <l>He's madder ſtill —</l>
                     <l>Hold Sir! I will fight —</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fen.</speaker>
                     <l>Then thou art Generous, and I'll deſtroy</l>
                     <l>Thy tainted life with ſo much gallantry,</l>
                     <l>'Twill be leſs happineſs to live then dye,</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <pb n="34" facs="tcp:199207:22"/>
                     <speaker>Alon.</speaker>
                     <l>Firſt hear my Reaſon, though your own you ſlight</l>
                     <l>Nay hear me ſpeak, or elſe I will not fight.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fen.</speaker>
                     <p>Say on —</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Alon.</speaker>
                     <l>The Crime you charge me with is Love,</l>
                     <l>But 'tis the ſtrangeſt Love that man can own,</l>
                     <l>To doat upon a Beauty yet unknown:</l>
                     <l>An object, which ne'r entertain'd my Eyes,</l>
                     <l>Nor fancy yet, — O ſenſleſs jealouſies!</l>
                     <l>Time is not, two houres older grown ſince fame</l>
                     <l>Firſt reach'd my Eares with your <hi>Alcindas</hi> name.</l>
                     <l>Have you ſuch pow'rful Rhet'rick, to enforce</l>
                     <l>So ſtrange a paſſion with your mad diſcourſe?</l>
                     <l>She never had a thought, nor wiſh from me,</l>
                     <l>But what I paid as one concern'd for thee.</l>
                     <l>Believe thy friend, recal thy wandring ſenſe,</l>
                     <l>Own thy miſtake, and ſee my Innocence.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fen.</speaker>
                     <l>Ye drouzy ſtars! how long will yee permit,</l>
                     <l>That I ſuch groſs abſurdities commit?</l>
                     <l>Thou cruel Woman, and more cruel Fate,</l>
                     <l>Am I the mark of Loves, and Fortunes hate?</l>
                     <l>Forgive me Sir! and if y'are yet my friend,</l>
                     <l>Helpe me to give my Love and care an end.</l>
                     <l>Peirce this rebellious heart, one little thruſt</l>
                     <l>Will pay deaths tribute; then my peaceful duſt</l>
                     <l>Wrapp'd in the cold imbraces of the grave,</l>
                     <l>Where it can nothing wiſh, will all things have.</l>
                     <l>Turn not away — will you be cruel too?</l>
                     <l>Why ſhould I beg what I my ſelf can do</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Offers to fall on his Sword.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Alon.</speaker>
                     <p>Strange madneſs! — Heavens! what do you intend —</p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Alonzo <hi>hinders him.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fen.</speaker>
                     <p>To ſpight my fortune, are not you my friend?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Alon.</speaker>
                     <p>I'll ſeale it with my deareſt blood.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fen.</speaker>
                     <l>Then why</l>
                     <l>Will you oppoſe my lateſt remedy?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Alon.</speaker>
                     <l>How can death be the end of miſerie,</l>
                     <l>When 'tis the greateſt pain of all to dye?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <pb n="35" facs="tcp:199207:22"/>
                     <speaker>Fen.</speaker>
                     <p>O death is ſhort, and after there's no pain;</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Alon.</speaker>
                     <l>But when we dye we hope to live again,</l>
                     <l>You rob the gods of their prerogative,</l>
                     <l>If you ſhould dye when they would have you live.</l>
                     <l>By acts ſo deſperate, and ſo injuſt,</l>
                     <l>You will renew your ſorrows in the duſt.</l>
                     <l>Be yet your ſelf, bravely reſolve to ſlight</l>
                     <l>The worſt effects of Loves, and Fortunes ſpight.</l>
                     <l>He rules his ſtars, though never ſo unkind,</l>
                     <l>That bears misfortunes with an equal mind.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fen.</speaker>
                     <l>Ye pow'rs above! pity my ſad Eſtate:</l>
                     <l>And guide me th'rough this Labyrinth of Fate.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Exeunt</hi> Don Feniſe <hi>and</hi> Alonzo.</stage>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="scene">
                  <head>Scene 3.</head>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Enter</hi> Laraſco, <hi>with three Neighbours.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Lar.</speaker>
                     <l>No quarrels Gentlemen! that's my decree,</l>
                     <l>For I'm a Tyrant if you anger me:</l>
                     <l>A Lyon incarnate — for the leaſt word,</l>
                     <l>I muſt have ſatisfaction with the ſword.</l>
                     <l>This <hi>Bilboe,</hi> ſimple as it hangs, has ſped</l>
                     <l>Whole dozens in a morning at <hi>Madrid.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Heark ye! this bold <hi>French</hi> boy that made ſuch work</l>
                     <l>In <hi>Flanders,</hi> and the huge <hi>Venetian Turk.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Both pay a penſion to this dreadful Sword —</l>
                     <l>You know more then the King does; not a Word —</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>1. <hi>Neigh.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <p>O wonderful how ſtrongly is he made?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>2. <hi>Neigh.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <p>Well we are bleſt to meet this noble blade.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Lar.</speaker>
                     <l>The King imployes ſo many flatt'ring Spies,</l>
                     <l>I could not reſt but for this baſe diſguiſe.</l>
                     <l>You are all true —</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>
                        <hi>All.</hi> 3.</speaker>
                     <p>I! I! I! —</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Lar.</speaker>
                     <l>Nay were you baſe,</l>
                     <l>Not one of you ſhould live to leave this place.</l>
                     <l>Would you be Souldiers? men of great command?</l>
                     <l>Shew but a line from this victorious hand</l>
                     <pb n="36" facs="tcp:199207:23"/>
                     <l>Though I'm ſo feirce; ſometimes I'm pleaſant too,</l>
                     <l>And fool with mortals, as I dance with you.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>The <hi>Dance</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Lar.</speaker>
                     <l>Hold! hold! this boxing may my courage raiſe,</l>
                     <l>Which only blood and gapeing wounds alaies.</l>
                     <l>When the dog <hi>Turk</hi> was at <hi>Lepanto</hi> beat,</l>
                     <l>Who was it think ye gave him that defeat?</l>
                     <l>The wings were loſt, the plain with dead was fill'd,</l>
                     <l>The Cannon taken and the body reeld,</l>
                     <l>But never was there ſo much horrour ſeen,</l>
                     <l>As when my ſingle troop of horſe fell in.</l>
                     <l>Th'rough Guns, Swords, fire and blood I led the way,</l>
                     <l>Ralli'd the flying troops and won the day.</l>
                     <l>The <hi>Turkes</hi> like fearful ſheep we overcame,</l>
                     <l>You could not hear the Cannons for my name,</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Laraſco! Laraſco! Victoria!</hi>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>All.</speaker>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Laraſco! Victoria! Laraſco!</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Enter</hi> Feniſe <hi>and</hi> Alonzo.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fen.</speaker>
                     <p>Sirrah! what ſaucy noiſe is this I hear?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Neighbors run off.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Lar.</speaker>
                     <p>Only a little harmeleſs muſick Sir —</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fen.</speaker>
                     <l>Haſte, haſte, <hi>Laraſco!</hi> and prepare my horſe;</l>
                     <l>To your advice I now will have recourſe.</l>
                     <l>Woman farewel! Glory and Fame I'll court;</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Alonzo!</hi> ſee her not, the time's too ſhort:</l>
                     <l>My paſſion may revive by longer ſtay.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Alon.</speaker>
                     <l>Bravely reſolv'd —</l>
                     <l>When you are ready, I'll ſoon lead the way <stage>
                           <hi>Exit</hi> Feniſe.</stage>
                     </l>
                     <l>This murth'ring beauty I muſt needs ſurvey</l>
                     <l>What's your bus'neſs here?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Enter</hi> Sanchez.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>San.</speaker>
                     <l>Hearing that you wanted a man I came,</l>
                     <pb n="37" facs="tcp:199207:23"/>
                     <l>To tender my ſervice to you</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Alon.</speaker>
                     <p>Where haſt thou liv'd?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>San.</speaker>
                     <l>I ſerv'd a wealthy man in <hi>India</hi> laſt:</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Signior Don Pedro</hi> —</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Alon.</speaker>
                     <p>
                        <hi>De Valiza</hi> was't?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>San.</speaker>
                     <p>The ſame; I ſerv'd him 'till his lateſt breath.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Alon.</speaker>
                     <p>Why, he was ſhiprack'd; how did'ſt thou 'ſcape death?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>San.</speaker>
                     <l>No Sir he did at Sea pay Natures debt —</l>
                     <l>So good a maſter, I ſhall ne'r forget.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Alon.</speaker>
                     <l>Canſt tell what Port the Veſſel made, and where</l>
                     <l>Thoſe little Ladies are, which he had there.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>San.</speaker>
                     <l>The ſhip arriv'd in <hi>Spain,</hi> I know no more;</l>
                     <l>I was next day found dead upon the ſhore:</l>
                     <l>My ſenſe ſo long was loſt, I ne'r did know</l>
                     <l>How I came there, or who had us'd me ſo.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Alon.</speaker>
                     <l>I'll take thee for that Maſters ſake, go in</l>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>Exit</hi> Sanchez.</stage>
                     <l>This news will much upon <hi>Don Feniſe</hi> win,</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Don Pedra de Valiza</hi> was my Father;</l>
                     <l>One of the Ladies was ſiſter to <hi>Don Feniſe,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>The other was my ſiſter.</l>
                     <l>Nine years they have been miſſing, and 'till now</l>
                     <l>We never heard where they were loſt, or how —</l>
                     <l>Grant they may yet ſurvive, ye powr's divine!</l>
                     <l>Then <hi>Feniſe</hi> is oblig'd by vows to mine,</l>
                     <l>And I'm as ſtrictly ty'd to marry his:</l>
                     <l>Which will confirm his thoughts of quitting this.</l>
                     <l>I will not ſee her, but wee'l ſtrait to horſe:</l>
                     <l>And yet I muſt, compel'd by hidden force —</l>
                     <l>What ſhould this mean Devil! to let thee ſee,</l>
                     <l>None of thy female ſprights have pow'r o're me.</l>
                     <l>I will go ſee her; Woman do thy worſt!</l>
                     <l>Who courts, or feares thee, equally is curſt.</l>
                  </sp>
               </div>
               <trailer>The End of the Third Act.</trailer>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="act">
               <pb n="38" facs="tcp:199207:24"/>
               <head>ACT IV.</head>
               <div n="1" type="scene">
                  <head>Scene 1.</head>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Enter</hi> Don Feniſe <hi>and</hi> Don Alonzo.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fen.</speaker>
                     <l>How! our ſiſters, and on the coaſt of <hi>Spain!</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Each hour's an age 'till you return again.</l>
                     <l>If fair <hi>Laurina</hi> lives, once more I vow,</l>
                     <l>On none but her I will my heart beſtow.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Alon.</speaker>
                     <l>May all the curſes of the <hi>Trojan</hi> Queen,</l>
                     <l>Upon my head be doubl'd ore agen,</l>
                     <l>If any beauty living has a part</l>
                     <l>But my <hi>Caliſta,</hi> in <hi>Alonzo's</hi> heart.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fen.</speaker>
                     <l>Wee'l ſearch where careful mortals never trod.</l>
                     <l>Where birds or ſullen beaſts make no aboad —</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Alon.</speaker>
                     <p>No melancholy grove, — no hollow tree —</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fen.</speaker>
                     <l>No Creek i'th' briney region of the Sea —</l>
                     <l>Though deep as hell, ſecret as luſtful night,</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Alon.</speaker>
                     <p>Or traytors thoughts —</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fen.</speaker>
                     <p>Shall 'ſcape our peirceing ſight.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Alon.</speaker>
                     <p>I'll find <hi>Caliſta</hi> —</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fen.</speaker>
                     <p>And <hi>Laurina</hi> I —</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Alon.</speaker>
                     <p>Wee'll in a bed or grave together lie.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Exeunt</hi> Feniſe <hi>and</hi> Alonzo.</stage>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="scene">
                  <head>Scene 2.</head>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Enter</hi> Don Manuel <hi>and</hi> Alcinda, <hi>in</hi> Don Manuel's <hi>Houſe.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Man.</speaker>
                     <l>Your Genius fair <hi>Alcinda!</hi> takes a flight,</l>
                     <l>Above the common reach of Womens ſight.</l>
                     <l>You are diſcreet, and can inſtruct me beſt,</l>
                     <l>How to reſolve a doubt which breaks my reſt.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Alc.</speaker>
                     <p>Good Sir ſpare my bluſhes: What is my crime?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Man.</speaker>
                     <l>Lay by-ſuch thoughts, for I would loſe no time —</l>
                     <l>Pray hear me!</l>
                     <pb n="39" facs="tcp:199207:24"/>
                     <l>Suppoſe a harmleſs child were left alone,</l>
                     <l>Wandring and loſt upon ſome pathleſs down.</l>
                     <l>Forſaken by her Parents, and expos'd</l>
                     <l>To fortunes mercy; this is but ſuppos'd —</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Alc.</speaker>
                     <p>No parents could poſſeſs ſuch flinty minds.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Man.</speaker>
                     <l>A gentleman this little wand'rer finds,</l>
                     <l>Dejected, weary, hopeleſs, ſtarv'd, and weak,</l>
                     <l>Where none could ſee her weep, or hear her ſpeak.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Alc.</speaker>
                     <p>O Heavens! would he not relieve the child?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Man.</speaker>
                     <l>Neceſſity already made her wild:</l>
                     <l>He kindly takes her up, and brings her home.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Alc.</speaker>
                     <l>A noble pious man, Ages to come</l>
                     <l>Will bleſs his Charity —</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Man.</speaker>
                     <l>Pray hear the reſt!</l>
                     <l>She with his daughter ſhares his equal breſt:</l>
                     <l>Their cloathes alike, alike their breeding is,</l>
                     <l>Onely his thoughts diſtinguiſh'd that from this.</l>
                     <l>Suppoſe my ſelf the man, and you were ſhe,</l>
                     <l>Imagine it; how would you anſwer me?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Alc.</speaker>
                     <l>As Heaven Sir! and juſtice do command,</l>
                     <l>My heart would not permit you to demand,</l>
                     <l>But I ſhould freely offer what you gave;</l>
                     <l>To buy your liberty, become a ſlave.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Man.</speaker>
                     <l>Then know, that you are ſhe: that child whom I</l>
                     <l>Found ſo caſt off to want, and miſerie:</l>
                     <l>'Twas I preſerv'd you; what has ſince befel,</l>
                     <l>How I have lov'd you, your own ſelf can tell.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Alc.</speaker>
                     <l>You tell me wonders Sir! why did you name</l>
                     <l>Your ſelf my guardian?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Man,</speaker>
                     <l>Thy ſpotleſs fame</l>
                     <l>Had elſe been blaſted, with the buſie air</l>
                     <l>Of envious tongues, which nothing can repair.</l>
                     <l>Beſides, <hi>Roſella</hi> juſtly might repine,</l>
                     <l>To ſee her welfare pris'd no more then thine.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Alc.</speaker>
                     <l>Good Sir! informe me who my Parents were,</l>
                     <l>Whoſe hopeleſs ſtate forc'd them to leave me there</l>
                     <l>With bended knees, low as the humble earth,</l>
                     <l>I'd pay that duty which I owe my birth.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <pb n="40" facs="tcp:199207:25"/>
                     <speaker>Man.</speaker>
                     <l>Some Oracle muſt anſwer your requeſt,</l>
                     <l>But if that tenderneſs I have expreſt,</l>
                     <l>Deſerve your grateful thoughts, if ought be due,</l>
                     <l>Reſtore me back that life I then gave you.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Alc.</speaker>
                     <l>Explain your ſecret language Sir! from me</l>
                     <l>You may command my life, and liberty!</l>
                     <l>With careful duty I'll your care repay,</l>
                     <l>My narrow fate permits no other way.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Man.</speaker>
                     <l>In ſhort, Love has ſo far poſſes't my mind,</l>
                     <l>I cannot live unleſs you will be kind.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Alc.</speaker>
                     <l>Heavens! what do I hear? exceſs of care</l>
                     <l>Deſturbs your ſenſe, you are not well I fear.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Man.</speaker>
                     <l>Nouriſh no more this idle misbelief,</l>
                     <l>Let your reply be poſitive, and brief;</l>
                     <l>I love you, to enjoy you, come be wiſe,</l>
                     <l>My cloſet's private from the Worlds eyes;</l>
                     <l>None dares diſturb our joyes, and what's unknown,</l>
                     <l>Untold by babling fame, is ſtill undone.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Alc.</speaker>
                     <l>O Sir! can you find out a privacy,</l>
                     <l>Shut from the ſight of Heavens peircing eye?</l>
                     <l>That will behold us, and though juſtice ſtayes,</l>
                     <l>'Twill grow the more ſevere by thoſe delayes.</l>
                     <l>Divine revenge will ſeize you, in a time</l>
                     <l>When y'are purſuing this unhappy crime;</l>
                     <l>Nor can it be unknown, the dazling ſun</l>
                     <l>Will write upon my forehead what is done.</l>
                     <l>Thus low I beg your pity — O forbear!</l>
                     <l>Your guilt will like a gnawing Vultur, tear</l>
                     <l>Your fright'ned Conſcience; and the action paſt,</l>
                     <l>The beaſtly pleaſure dies: the guilt will laſt.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Man.</speaker>
                     <l>Fairly accept my love and my eſtate,</l>
                     <l>Or I'll enjoy you at a cheaper rate.</l>
                     <l>I'll force your ſtubborn wilfulneſs, and then</l>
                     <l>Return you to your vagrant life ag'en.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Alc.</speaker>
                     <l>Turn me a beging Sir! and I'll proclame</l>
                     <l>You for a Saint, I'll canonzie your name.</l>
                     <l>You cannot force me though I am your ſlave,</l>
                     <l>Death will preſerve me and my honour ſave.</l>
                     <pb n="41" facs="tcp:199207:25"/>
                     <l>Juſt Heaven! hear my vow, if you proceed,</l>
                     <l>May I be curs'd, if I ſurvive the dead.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Man.</speaker>
                     <l>I'll take no more, ſo cruel and ſo young!</l>
                     <l>Force ſhall ſupply the weakneſs of my tongue.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Alcinda <hi>runs out at one dore, and</hi> Mingo <hi>enters haſtily at another, diſguis'd.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Alc.</speaker>
                     <p>Help! help! help!</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Man.</speaker>
                     <p>Croſs luck! ſpeak what art thou?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Min.</speaker>
                     <p>It is the ſame; dear miſchief help me now!</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Man.</speaker>
                     <p>Whether would'ſt go? what do'ſt ſeek? what do'ſt fear?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Min.</speaker>
                     <l>Moſt noble Sir! afford your curteous ear,</l>
                     <l>The chance of War, guided by fates decree,</l>
                     <l>Made me a ſlave to Turkiſh tyranie.</l>
                     <l>I ſerv'd a 'prentiſhip in chayns, became</l>
                     <l>An Eunuch to aſſiſt their beaſtly flames:</l>
                     <l>Kind Heav'n at laſt appeas'd, did freedom grant,</l>
                     <l>But in my flight I was ſurpris'd by want.</l>
                     <l>Some envious females having known my caſe,</l>
                     <l>And all my loſſes, had me ſtrait in Chaſe.</l>
                     <l>I took this Sanctuary, and from you</l>
                     <l>Entreat protection from this rageing crew.</l>
                     <l>By all you value moſt, by all that's dear;</l>
                     <l>And by your Innocence preſerve me here.</l>
                     <l>On your ſweet mercies Altar I lay hold,</l>
                     <l>No diſreſpect but danger makes me bold.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Man.</speaker>
                     <p>But art thou a very Eunuch indeed?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Min.</speaker>
                     <p>As I tell true, ſo may you help my need.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Man.</speaker>
                     <l>I'll entertain thee, if thou wilt be mine,</l>
                     <l>Thy bus'neſs ſhall be eaſie.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Min.</speaker>
                     <l>I reſigne,</l>
                     <l>My life t'ee, and if I've done ill in ought,</l>
                     <l>My diligence ſhall expiate my fault.</l>
                     <l>I have him faſt; He's full of thoughts, plot on</l>
                     <l>Projecting Scot! thou fool! thou cheating Don! <stage>Aſide.</stage>
                     </l>
                     <l>Bleſt ſaints reward you, you have ſav'd my life.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Man.</speaker>
                     <l>This Eunuchs help will ſoon conclude the ſtrife,</l>
                     <l>I'll in and teach him how to play his part,</l>
                     <l>Her body's mine, although I loſe her heart.</l>
                     <l>Follow me in — <stage>
                           <hi>Exeunt</hi> Manuel <hi>and</hi> Mingo.</stage>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="scene">
                  <pb n="42" facs="tcp:199207:26"/>
                  <head>Scene 3.</head>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Enter</hi> Roſella, Alcinda, Leonella.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Roſel.</speaker>
                     <p>A raviſher! O ſtrange and horrid Crime!</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Alc.</speaker>
                     <l>'Tis a ſad truth, if at that very time,</l>
                     <l>Heav'n had not ſent that unexpected aid;</l>
                     <l>His Luſt moſt fiercely rag'd, when moſt I pray'd.</l>
                     <l>Oh that <hi>Don Feniſe</hi> would agen be kind!</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Leon.</speaker>
                     <l>Madam! ne'r hope that he will change his mind;</l>
                     <l>You eaſily may gueſs at his intent,</l>
                     <l>By this fine ſong his worthy friend has ſent.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Roſel.</speaker>
                     <p>Sing it <hi>Leonella</hi> —</p>
                  </sp>
                  <q>
                     <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                        <body>
                           <div type="song">
                              <stage>
                                 <hi>Leonella</hi> ſings this Song.</stage>
                              <lg>
                                 <l>Down with this Love that has made ſuch a pother,</l>
                                 <l>This Jack with a Lanthorn that leads us a round,</l>
                                 <l>'Till with dull Marri'ge we Cheat one another,</l>
                                 <l>For joyes that do vaniſh, as ſoon as th'are found.</l>
                                 <l>Repent ye proud Nymphs! for your Tricks ſhall not paſs,</l>
                                 <l>We'll change no more Gold, and good Stones for your Glaſs.</l>
                              </lg>
                              <lg>
                                 <l>While ſo ſeverely you rail at the pleaſure,</l>
                                 <l>And kill the poor Lover that's at your command;</l>
                                 <l>Like Doctors, you turn your heads from the Treaſure,</l>
                                 <l>But Oh how you graſp what is put in your hand.</l>
                                 <l>Repent, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                                 </l>
                              </lg>
                              <lg>
                                 <l>When the ſhort minute we ſigh'd for is over,</l>
                                 <l>The Nymph is more kind, and more brisk than before;</l>
                                 <l>But how dejected and dull is her Lover,</l>
                                 <l>To find all his Paſſion can purchaſe no more?</l>
                                 <l>Repent ye proud Nymphs! for your Tricks ſhall not paſs,</l>
                                 <l>We'll change no more Gold, and good Stones for your Glaſs.</l>
                              </lg>
                           </div>
                        </body>
                     </floatingText>
                  </q>
                  <sp>
                     <pb n="43" facs="tcp:199207:26"/>
                     <speaker>Roſel.</speaker>
                     <l>Let not her raſh deſpair invade thy heart,</l>
                     <l>Continue kind, and let me play my part.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Leon.</speaker>
                     <p>Madam! here's a meſſenger from <hi>Don Feniſe.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Roſel.</speaker>
                     <l>My life on't he repents; withdraw a while,</l>
                     <l>When you return my news ſhall make ye ſmile. <stage>
                           <hi>Exit</hi> Alcinda.</stage>
                     </l>
                     <l>I'll puniſh him; go fetch my Vizard maſk,</l>
                     <l>And tell him I'm <hi>Alcinda</hi> if he ask.</l>
                     <l>Now bring him in;</l>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>Enter</hi> Alonzo.</stage>
                     <l>Reaſon protect my heart!</l>
                     <l>A ſweeter ſhape was never feign'd by art.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Alin.</speaker>
                     <l>Muſt I diſcourſe with masks? with ſableſhrouds?</l>
                     <l>I dare peruſe your beauty free from clouds.</l>
                     <l>Could you outſhine the morning, could your rayes</l>
                     <l>Obſcure the glorious ſun in cleareſt dayes;</l>
                     <l>Could your inſinuating flames, inſpire</l>
                     <l>A Stoicks flinty heart with loves ſoft fire:</l>
                     <l>To me your boaſted Excellence is dim,</l>
                     <l>Thoſe fooliſh toyes have pow'r on none but him,</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Feniſe,</hi> that lov'd you once, mark me Lady!</l>
                     <l>That lov'd you once, and ſuch a Beauty made ye;</l>
                     <l>But he's converted, and he vows, no more</l>
                     <l>Your well mix'd paint and patches to adore.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Roſ.</speaker>
                     <p>Pray hear me Sir! —</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Alon.</speaker>
                     <l>Madam! I am not come</l>
                     <l>To feign ſad ſtories of your ſervants death;</l>
                     <l>Your charming name fil'd up his lateſt breath,</l>
                     <l>He dy'd for love of you, — and when your tears</l>
                     <l>Witneſs repentance, Eaſe you of your fears.</l>
                     <l>No! I reſolv'd ſome minutes to beſtow,</l>
                     <l>To ſlight thoſe charmes that had bewitch'd him ſo. <stage>
                           <hi>Exit</hi> Alonzo.</stage>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Roſ.</speaker>
                     <l>As you are truly Noble hear me ſpeak;</l>
                     <l>Should he be cruel, ſure my heart muſt break.</l>
                     <l>Is he gone? quickly call him back, run, fly —</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Leon.</speaker>
                     <p>'Slife what ailes you Madam?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Roſ.</speaker>
                     <l>Make no reply —</l>
                     <pb n="44" facs="tcp:199207:27"/>
                     <l>Perſwade him back, or never ſee my face;</l>
                     <l>Ha! what have I done? in ſo ſhort a ſpace</l>
                     <l>To loſe my heart?</l>
                     <l>This for <hi>Alcinda</hi> I did undertake,</l>
                     <l>Now ſhe may do it for <hi>Roſellas</hi> ſake.</l>
                     <l>A gallant man!</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Enter</hi> Alonzo.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Alon.</speaker>
                     <p>What does your meſſage mean?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Roſel.</speaker>
                     <l>Reallity, let <hi>Feniſe</hi> love ag'en, <stage>She takes off her mask.</stage>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Alcinda</hi> ſhall be his; I give my hand,</l>
                     <l>A ſign the contract ſhall moſt firmly ſtand.</l>
                     <l>Uſe all the intereſt that you can make</l>
                     <l>To ſtay him, for the ſad <hi>Alcindas</hi> ſake.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Alon.</speaker>
                     <l>Ha! what do I ſee?</l>
                     <l>Angel! or Saint! or whatſoe'r you be!</l>
                     <l>That take frail Womans ſhape, low on the ground,</l>
                     <l>I beg that pardon you from Heaven found.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Leon.</speaker>
                     <l>The gentleman's ſmitt'n, he's caught i'faith!</l>
                     <l>How he ſurveyes each beauty that ſhe hath?</l>
                     <l>'Tis <hi>German</hi> clockwork ſure, how its eyes roul?</l>
                     <l>Look ye the mouth on't moves; alas pretty Soul!</l>
                     <l>A very rare motion —</l>
                     <l>I long to ſee ſome tricks, his peirceing eye</l>
                     <l>Declares him Skilful in Aſtrologie;</l>
                     <l>Can you caſt nativities Sir?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Alon.</speaker>
                     <l>Begone!</l>
                     <l>Let me and my nativity alone —</l>
                     <l>O happy friend!</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Roſel.</speaker>
                     <l>Near night he'l find her at the Cypreſs grove;</l>
                     <l>He will not fail if he pretend to love.</l>
                     <l>Good thoughts attend you —</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Alon.</speaker>
                     <l>Though you deſign</l>
                     <l>Your ſelf for him, your picture may be mine —</l>
                     <l>Think me not rude, by your fair ſelf I vow,</l>
                     <l>I ne'r beg'd favour from your Sex 'till now.</l>
                     <pb n="45" facs="tcp:199207:27"/>
                     <l>The <hi>Indies</hi> ſhall not buy it from my eyes —</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Roſ.</speaker>
                     <l>Though what you ask my modeſty denies,</l>
                     <l>Nay though I've made a vow never to part</l>
                     <l>From this, but to the man that has my heart —</l>
                     <l>Yet y'have prevail'd; take it, and all content.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Alon.</speaker>
                     <p>As I would take aguift from Heaven ſent.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Roſ.</speaker>
                     <l>Oh my heart! farewel Sir! — pray don't forget,</l>
                     <l>Fie, fie, <hi>Roſella!</hi> this once — he's there yet —</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Exeunt</hi> Alonzo <hi>and</hi> Roſella <hi>at ſeveral dores.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Enter preſently</hi> Alonzo <hi>and</hi> Mingo.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Alon.</speaker>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Mingo!</hi> why this diſguiſe? what mak'ſt thou here?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Min.</speaker>
                     <l>I ſtrive to live — y, are angry ſtill I fear.</l>
                     <l>Pray pardon me; you alwayes found me juſt.</l>
                     <l>In your affairs, though led aſide by luſt.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Alon.</speaker>
                     <l>Pry'thee no more, leſt Proteſtations raiſe</l>
                     <l>Suſpition of thy faith, without a cauſe.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Min.</speaker>
                     <l>Now Sir! I am from all my faults reclaim'd,</l>
                     <l>And bluſh with anger when I hear them nam'd.</l>
                     <l>Pray let me ſerve you here Sir! my great care</l>
                     <l>Shall teſtifie, what my intentions are.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Alon.</speaker>
                     <p>I'll think upon't; there's earneſt of my love. <stage>gives him mony.</stage>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Min.</speaker>
                     <l>May you receive this bounty from above, <stage>
                           <hi>Exit</hi> Alonzo.</stage>
                     </l>
                     <l>In ten thouſand Curſes; and when Heavens ſtore</l>
                     <l>Exauſted is, I'll coyn as many more.</l>
                     <l>This was a happy diſguiſe —</l>
                     <l>I've gain'd ſo much upon <hi>Don Manuel's</hi> wife,</l>
                     <l>She has diſcover'd to me all his life.</l>
                     <l>He's mine, to gain <hi>Alcinda</hi> by my Ayd;</l>
                     <l>And my pretended Love has gain'd the maid.</l>
                     <l>From her I'll lrarn what brought <hi>Alonzo</hi> on,</l>
                     <l>And then I'll do your work, my angry <hi>Don!</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Here ſhe comes —</l>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>Enter</hi> Leonella.</stage>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>Enter</hi> Don Manuel <hi>obſerving them.</hi>
                     </stage>
                     <l>O my dear Rogue! what dangers have I trod?</l>
                     <l>How many weary ſteps? how often rode</l>
                     <pb n="46" facs="tcp:199207:28"/>
                     <l>Ore hill and dale? through fire and froſt.</l>
                     <l>Through frights and foes? what Wives? what fortunes loſt?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Leon.</speaker>
                     <p>Time has not chang'd thee, thou art <hi>Mingo</hi> ſtill.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mingo.</speaker>
                     <l>Thy ſlave my Sultaneſs! both heart and will:</l>
                     <l>O let me ever hold thee thus —</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Man.</speaker>
                     <l>Here's ſport! —</l>
                     <l>An Eunuch? a Stalion! I'll ſpoyl your Court.</l>
                     <l>D'ee hear Sirrah! Villain! Rogue! what are you?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Exit</hi> Leonella.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Min.</speaker>
                     <l>Thy evil Angel, <hi>Gorzell!</hi> nay tis true:</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Gorzell</hi> I ſay! haſt thou forgot thy name?</l>
                     <l>Thy Cheats, thy Murthers too, I can proclame,</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Man.</speaker>
                     <p>Mercy, ſweet Devil mercy! pity me!</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Min.</speaker>
                     <l>Riſe mortal, and give ear to my decree;</l>
                     <l>One beauty ſhall be mine, the other thine,</l>
                     <l>And equally we'll ſhare the pilfer'd coyn;</l>
                     <l>Diſpatch thy anſwer quick; conſent, and live —</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Man.</speaker>
                     <p>Y'are merciful, take all that I can give.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Min.</speaker>
                     <p>Then I'm thy friend, and <hi>Mingo.</hi> 
                        <stage>Diſcovers himſelf.</stage>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Man.</speaker>
                     <l>Catch'd agen?</l>
                     <l>'Sdeath how didſt thou diſcover, me or when?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Min.</speaker>
                     <l>O never queſtion that, let it ſuffice,</l>
                     <l>I know you now, and all your Subtleties.</l>
                     <l>Hold to your bargain, we'll go hand in hand,</l>
                     <l>And raiſe ſuch plots Fate ſhall not countermand.</l>
                     <l>That wench will tell me news if you retire —</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Man.</speaker>
                     <p>Th'art my good Angel, take thy own deſire.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Min.</speaker>
                     <l>You muſt not ſee it, though I ſeem too kind</l>
                     <l>To your <hi>Tereſa</hi> —</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Man.</speaker>
                     <p>No! no! uſe thy mind — <stage>
                           <hi>Exit</hi> Manuel.</stage>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Min.</speaker>
                     <l>Yes, and thy ſoft pate, long proſperity</l>
                     <l>Has lull'd the raſcal in ſecurity.</l>
                     <l>Here comes his fellow trader —</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Enter</hi> Tereſa.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ter.</speaker>
                     <p>Dear Eunuch! this has been a tedious day.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Min.</speaker>
                     <l>How eagerly this Creature longs for prey?</l>
                     <pb n="47" facs="tcp:199207:28"/>
                     <l>Time's lazy grown, 'tis yet an hour to night.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ter.</speaker>
                     <l>That hour's eternity — let's loſe our ſight,</l>
                     <l>And make it ever night —</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Min.</speaker>
                     <p>O hold! you propheſie your death I fear.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ter.</speaker>
                     <p>Death! prythee let's go in — and meet it there.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Min.</speaker>
                     <l>Know then in ſhort,</l>
                     <l>I'm hir'd to murther you; here's earneſt for't:</l>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>Shews the money</hi> Alonzo <hi>gave him.</hi>
                     </stage>
                     <l>Your husband loves <hi>Alcinda</hi> —</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ter.</speaker>
                     <l>O baſe ſlave!</l>
                     <l>Villain! I'll to him ſtrait; I'll tear the knave —</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Min.</speaker>
                     <l>Stay! you'l undo us both; but if you will,</l>
                     <l>You may preſerve us both, and <hi>Manuel</hi> kill.</l>
                     <l>Diſpatch him roundly, if you love me then</l>
                     <l>I'll marry you —</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ter.</speaker>
                     <p>I'll doe't! thou beſt of men! <stage>
                           <hi>Exit</hi> Tereſa.</stage>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Leonella <hi>peeps in and Enters.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Min.</speaker>
                     <l>Nay ſhe's gone;</l>
                     <l>My beſt ſaint! my wiſe <hi>Medea!</hi> what ſpell</l>
                     <l>Wilt thou invent, old <hi>Manuel's</hi> rage to quell?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Leon.</speaker>
                     <p>A powerful charm which he can ne'r withſtand.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Min.</speaker>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Tereſa</hi> doats, doats on me, by this hand!</l>
                     <l>She's ſo jealous of thee too, we ſhall ne'r</l>
                     <l>Enjoy in quiet while we tarry here.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Leon.</speaker>
                     <l>Come, come, there's Villany on foot; my ear</l>
                     <l>Gave me intellgence, though none appear.</l>
                     <l>They look like ſaints; for all their pious ſhow,</l>
                     <l>There may be Murthers, Whores, and Rogues, or ſo.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Min.</speaker>
                     <l>I underſtand, therefore 'tis our beſt way,</l>
                     <l>To make a handſome pack, and march away.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Leon.</speaker>
                     <l>Our Ladies do prepare to meet their Loves,</l>
                     <l>I muſt along too —</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Min.</speaker>
                     <l>Mark well how it proves;</l>
                     <l>And let me know, it may produce a light,</l>
                     <l>To guide us on in our intended flight.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Leon.</speaker>
                     <p>I'll obſerve, adieu! —</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Min.</speaker>
                     <l>Ioy of my life, farewell! thus far I thrive;</l>
                     <pb n="46" facs="tcp:199207:29"/>
                     <l>I muſt be ſuddain, leſt ſo many Eyes</l>
                     <l>As I imploy, may find my Subtilties.</l>
                     <l>I'm ſtor'd with Wives, and with a helping friend,</l>
                     <l>I'll make true uſe o'm; to my propper end.</l>
                     <l>On fair <hi>Roſella</hi> lyes my aim, though here</l>
                     <l>Is my circumference, my centre's there.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Exit.</hi> Mingo.</stage>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="scene">
                  <head>Scene 4.</head>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Enter</hi> Alonzo, <hi>with a picture in his hand.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Alon.</speaker>
                     <lg>
                        <l>The blaſting light'ning darte from the Sky,</l>
                        <l>Kills not ſo ſure as this tranſpiercing Eye.</l>
                        <l>Coward <hi>Alonzo!</hi> ſhall thy Courage ſinck,</l>
                        <l>At white and red? a Woman make thee ſhrinck.</l>
                        <l>That thing which I deſpis'd; do I not know,</l>
                        <l>Beauties like flowr's do fade as faſt as grow?</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Why ſhould I love, and think of this? nay more,</l>
                        <l>That when we have enjoy'd, the paſſions o're,</l>
                        <l>And w'are aſham'd of that we did adore.</l>
                        <l>Unruly force of wild deſire! — this frame</l>
                        <l>Is beautiful as ſhe, this face the ſame,</l>
                        <l>This I can break, deform it when I pleaſe;</l>
                        <l>Intruding Age, or any weak diſeaſe,</l>
                        <l>Will make her pow'rful charms as ſoon decline;</l>
                        <l>Minds oft' are wicked, though the ſhapes divine.</l>
                        <l>Folly farewel! this Idle ſenceleſs toy,</l>
                        <l>And all my paſſion too, thus I deſtroy —</l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Alonzo <hi>throwes away the Picture,</hi> Feniſe <hi>Enters and takes it up.</hi> —</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fen.</speaker>
                     <p>What ſuddain change is this?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Alon.</speaker>
                     <l>O happy <hi>Feniſe!</hi> fair <hi>Alcinda's</hi> thine,</l>
                     <l>Fly to the Cypreſs grove, there ſhe'l reſign</l>
                     <l>Her ſelf into thy armes — be ever bleſt,</l>
                     <l>I'll ſeek a grave, while thou enjoy'ſt thy reſt.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <pb n="49" facs="tcp:199207:29"/>
                     <speaker>Fen.</speaker>
                     <l>Hate me for ever—</l>
                     <l>If I ſeek Joy while you have Diſcontent.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Alon.</speaker>
                     <l>I love your Miſtriſs Sir! and to prevent</l>
                     <l>Any unworthy Act, ſo baſe a flame</l>
                     <l>May tempt me to, I'le fly to hide my ſhame.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fen.</speaker>
                     <l>More unto Friendſhip, than to Love I ow,</l>
                     <l>If you unhappy are, I muſt be ſo.</l>
                     <l>You made her mine, when all my hope was gone,</l>
                     <l>'Tis juſt you ſhould enjoy what you have won.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Alon.</speaker>
                     <l>Let it ſuffice in Love I yield to you,</l>
                     <l>Strive not to conquer me in friendſhip too:</l>
                     <l>Conceal that tempting Shadow from my ſight;</l>
                     <l>Thoſe that would cure weak Eyes, ſhould fly the Light.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fen.</speaker>
                     <p>Is this the Form you love?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Alon.</speaker>
                     <l>No Painters Art,</l>
                     <l>Could e'r infuſe more life in ev'ry part.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fen.</speaker>
                     <l>Fortune is kind, her Bleſſings to divide,</l>
                     <l>Both may be happy yet, Both ſatisfi'd.</l>
                     <l>'Tis not <hi>Alcinda</hi> Sir! but may ſhe be</l>
                     <l>As kind, as fair <hi>Alcinda</hi> was to me.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Alon.</speaker>
                     <p>Who is it then? There was no other by.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fen.</speaker>
                     <l>Let's to the place, and there the difference try.</l>
                     <l>But ſtay they are here —</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Enter</hi> Alcinda, Roſella, Leonella.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Alon.</speaker>
                     <l>Two Suns at once in Beauties glorious Sphere,</l>
                     <l>Denote ſome change in Loves high State draws near.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fen.</speaker>
                     <p>Pray Heav'n his Tyranny may now decay.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Alon.</speaker>
                     <p>In me it ſhall, I'll die or win the day.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fen.</speaker>
                     <l>Encourag'd by your Goodneſs, I am come</l>
                     <l>To meet a Bleſſing, or receive my Doom.</l>
                     <l>More to my Love, then my Offence, is due;</l>
                     <l>My Change was feigned, but my Love is true.</l>
                     <l>It is the practice of the Pow'rs above,</l>
                     <l>To pardon Errors, and accept of Love:</l>
                     <l>Your Beautie's heav'nly, make your Language ſo:</l>
                     <l>Will you that pardon which you ask beſtow?</l>
                     <pb n="50" facs="tcp:199207:30"/>
                     <l>Though you ſo well your eaſie change diſguiſe,</l>
                     <l>I ſee the marks of Anger in your Eyes.</l>
                     <l>Remember <hi>Feniſe!</hi> you did uſe to wooe,</l>
                     <l>Deſpiſe not Love becauſe 'tis offer'd you.</l>
                     <l>Will you refuſe me then? Where ſhall I hide?</l>
                     <l>I bluſh to ask, but dye to be deny'd.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fen.</speaker>
                     <l>Refuſe you Madam! Will a ſwelling heart</l>
                     <l>Refuſe a Kingdom? Will a Hermit part</l>
                     <l>With want, and miſery? by his remove,</l>
                     <l>To ſhare the bleſſed happineſs above?</l>
                     <l>My Soul is ſo tranſported with her Bliſs,</l>
                     <l>I fear, it will believe no Heav'n but this.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Roſel.</speaker>
                     <p>But Fire that's ſlowly rais'd, as late decayes.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Alon.</speaker>
                     <l>Let common Beauties reign by common wayes:</l>
                     <l>Too much your Beauty, and my Love you wrong,</l>
                     <l>Light'ning is ſudden, yet no Flame more ſtrong.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Roſ.</speaker>
                     <p>Powder that ſwiftly fires, as ſoon does waſt.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Alon.</speaker>
                     <l>Yet does the Fire, as long's the Subject laſt.</l>
                     <l>So ſhall my Love, and never know decay,</l>
                     <l>But in the Grave, where no Affections ſtay.</l>
                     <l>That tedious way of Courtſhip you approve,</l>
                     <l>Shews much of Patience, and but little Love.</l>
                     <l>Extremes of Paſſion, ſuch as Love inſpires,</l>
                     <l>As ill are ſuffer'd, as devouring fires:</l>
                     <l>Mine, grown too pow'rful for my narrow Breaſt,</l>
                     <l>Preſumes already to diſturb your Reſt.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fen.</speaker>
                     <p>Madam! one charge from you, would make her yield.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Alc.</speaker>
                     <l>Love has the Day, but Shame would keep the Field.</l>
                     <l>Your heart is hers, pray truſt me with your hand,</l>
                     <l>Come Siſter! lend me yours, though <hi>Hymen</hi>'s Band</l>
                     <l>May be more Ceremonious, may this</l>
                     <l>Endure as long, and be as firm as his.</l>
                     <l>Now I pronounce you one—</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Roſel.</speaker>
                     <p>Remember Siſter! you compel my Love.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Alc.</speaker>
                     <p>The Earth ſhall vaniſh, e're my Faith remove.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Roſel.</speaker>
                     <l>With equal joy I meet your noble flame,</l>
                     <l>I will be ever yours — Pray hide my ſhame.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Alon.</speaker>
                     <l>That lovely bluſh, looks like the Ev'ning Air,</l>
                     <l>Whoſe Scarlet-dye proclaims the next day fair:</l>
                     <pb n="51" facs="tcp:199207:30"/>
                     <l>And ſo may this Prophetickly appear,</l>
                     <l>For here begins my bliſs, and ends my fear.</l>
                     <l>With purer Zeal a Heathen never paid</l>
                     <l>Vows to his Idol, for ſuppoſed Aid,</l>
                     <l>Then I preſent my Heart, a Gift too low</l>
                     <l>To ſpeak the Service I will ever owe.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fen.</speaker>
                     <l>Ladies! Since we are Conquerors thus far,</l>
                     <l>The great Affairs of Love, as thoſe of War,</l>
                     <l>Call for Advice to make the Conqueſt good.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Alon.</speaker>
                     <l>That from our Leaders muſt be underſtood.</l>
                     <l>Command us Ladies! We will execute.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Roſ.</speaker>
                     <p>This place is moſt unfit for ſuch diſpute.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Alc.</speaker>
                     <l>No Treaty will be heard, to think of that</l>
                     <l>Will be in vain, the Foe is obſtinate.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Alon.</speaker>
                     <l>Now let us lead you off a glorious Prize,</l>
                     <l>Why ſhould we truſt our fatal Deſtinies?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Roſel.</speaker>
                     <l>Brave Enemies! you ſhall command our Lives,</l>
                     <l>But haſty reſolution ſeldom thrives.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Alon.</speaker>
                     <l>My lovely Miſtriſs! where all Beauties dwell,</l>
                     <l>True honour of your worthy—Sex, farewel!</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Exeunt ſeveral wayes.</stage>
               </div>
               <div n="5" type="scene">
                  <head>Scene 5.</head>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Enter</hi> Don Manuel <hi>and</hi> Mingo.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ming.</speaker>
                     <l>Moſt certain 'tis they are reſolv'd to fly,</l>
                     <l>And only wait an Opportunity;</l>
                     <l>Pretend to make a Journey, and take Horſe;</l>
                     <l>'Tis Policy muſt do't, in vain is Force.</l>
                     <l>Now <hi>Leonella</hi> is diſpatch'd with that,</l>
                     <l>Shall raiſe between their Servants mortal hate.</l>
                     <l>They both ſhall die before to Morrows Sun;</l>
                     <l>Nay more, by their own Swords it ſhall be done.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Man.</speaker>
                     <p>Excellent <hi>Mingo!</hi> —</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ming.</speaker>
                     <l>With <hi>Leonella,</hi> I'me to meet this night,</l>
                     <l>I'th' Summer-houſe, for an intended flight.</l>
                     <l>That muſt be your Retreat, on her lay hold,</l>
                     <l>For ſhe'll be furniſh'd with a Mine of Gold.</l>
                     <pb n="52" facs="tcp:199207:31"/>
                     <l>Make haſte away! — be ſure you fail her not.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Man.</speaker>
                     <p>Wit proſper thee, brave Rogue! <stage>
                           <hi>Exit</hi> Manuel.</stage>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ming.</speaker>
                     <l>O fear it not.</l>
                     <l>Poor Fool! I'll make thee ſenſible e're long,</l>
                     <l>That thou haſt ſold thy Welfare for a Song.</l>
                     <l>An idle ſenſeleſs Tale, can thy dull Brain</l>
                     <l>Believe, that for thy eaſe I'll take this pain?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Enter</hi> Tereſa.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ming.</speaker>
                     <p>Here comes my Midnights Ghoſt—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Tereſ.</speaker>
                     <l>My beſt delight!</l>
                     <l>Fate can't deny us happineſs; this night</l>
                     <l>Old <hi>Manuel</hi> rides abroad.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ming.</speaker>
                     <p>But is it true?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Tereſ.</speaker>
                     <p>Juſt now we parted, as I came to you.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ming.</speaker>
                     <l>How Goodneſs is abus'd! a meer pretence;</l>
                     <l>How Rogues may work upon your Innocence?</l>
                     <l>Alas good Soul! This Night he means to ſpend</l>
                     <l>I'th' Summer-houſe, there's his long Journeys end:</l>
                     <l>There he, and modeſt <hi>Leonella</hi> meet.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Tereſ.</speaker>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Leonella</hi> too, bleſs me!</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ming.</speaker>
                     <l>Nay, go ſee't;</l>
                     <l>And if you love me, now you may be mine;</l>
                     <l>He once remov'd, I will be ever thine:</l>
                     <l>Here's that will do the work, revenge your wrong:</l>
                     <stage>Gives her a Piſtol and a Dagger.</stage>
                     <l>Reſolve it ſuddenly, the time's not long.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Tereſ.</speaker>
                     <l>Think not, my little Silence did proceed</l>
                     <l>From fooliſh pity, no! they both ſhall bleed.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ming.</speaker>
                     <p>The Woman you may pardon if you will.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Tereſ.</speaker>
                     <p>To rob me of thy love, no! both I'll kill.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ming.</speaker>
                     <p>My dear <hi>Infanta!</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Tereſ.</speaker>
                     <p>I'll do't! and meet thee in the Lodge, farewell!</p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Exit</hi> Tereſa.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ming.</speaker>
                     <l>Curſes purſue thee, how ſhe flyes to Hell?</l>
                     <l>This one Night paſt, to Morrow all's my own,</l>
                     <l>And this kind Wretch ſhall die for what I've done:</l>
                     <pb n="53" facs="tcp:199207:31"/>
                     <l>In Blood I'll wade ere <hi>Phebus</hi> leave his Bed,</l>
                     <l>And make my Crimes out-bluſh the Mornings red.</l>
                     <l>Great <hi>Nemeſis!</hi> refuſe me not thy Aid</l>
                     <l>Thy Sacrifice is loſt, if I'm betrai'd. <stage>Exit Mingo.</stage>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
               </div>
               <div n="6" type="scene">
                  <head>Scene 6.</head>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Enter</hi> Don Feniſe <hi>alone in his own Houſe.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fen.</speaker>
                     <l>How ſweet are all my Sorrows now! how dear</l>
                     <l>My Suffrings are, now Happineſs draws near!</l>
                     <l>Though in my Love I met with ſo much trouble,</l>
                     <l>My Pleaſure will be, as my Care was, double.</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Alonzo</hi> may have doubts, and jealous fears,</l>
                     <l>My long experience all ſuſpition clears.</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Roſella's</hi> Heart, like parched Straw, took fire,</l>
                     <l>And did as ſwiftly blaze into deſire:</l>
                     <l>Such flames are ſooneſt quench'd, and have leaſt heat;</l>
                     <l>My Happineſs as conſtant is as great;</l>
                     <l>Like noble Metal, which doth long repel</l>
                     <l>Aſſaulting Flames, that round about it dwell,</l>
                     <l>But once made hot, does long retain the fire,</l>
                     <l>So did my dear <hi>Alcinda</hi> meet deſire;</l>
                     <l>Her Love came ſlowly, but will ſure remain;</l>
                     <l>She will be conſtant, though I change again.</l>
                     <l>Moſt happy <hi>Feniſe!</hi> 
                        <stage>
                           <hi>Enter</hi> Leonella, <hi>and paſſing by him, careleſly drops a Letter.</hi>
                        </stage>
                     </l>
                     <l>Ha! ſure it was ſhe;</l>
                     <l>What makes ſhe here? Why ſhould ſhe fly from me?</l>
                     <l>This may inform me, (<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                           <desc>•••</desc>
                        </gap>y hearts delight</l>
                     <l>The brave <hi>Alonzo</hi>) pray Heav'n all is right!</l>
                     <l>Friendſhip allows me liberty to fee.</l>
                     <stage>He reads the Letter.</stage>
                     <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
                        <body>
                           <l>Fail not to meet me, as we did agree;</l>
                           <l>The hour preciſely Twelve, the place you know,</l>
                           <l>Blind <hi>Feniſe</hi> ſtill, no ſign of Friendſhip ſhow.</l>
                           <pb n="54" facs="tcp:199207:32"/>
                           <l>He may obſerve you with a Lovers Eye,</l>
                           <l>The time ſeems lazy now our joyes are nigh.</l>
                           <l>My dear <hi>Alonzo!</hi> haſte, you have my heart;</l>
                           <l>When once we meet again, we'll never part.</l>
                           <l>
                              <hi>Thine ever</hi> Alcinda.</l>
                        </body>
                     </floatingText>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Alcinda! Alcinda! Alcinda!</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>It cannot be, ſure my diſtemper'd Joy</l>
                     <l>Diſtracts my thoughts, and does my ſenſe deſtroy:</l>
                     <l>Or her fair ſhape which in my fancy lyes,</l>
                     <l>Sends bright reflections to abuſe my Eyes.</l>
                     <l>Ha! 'tis, by Heav'n 'tis ſo! And if it be, <stage>Leonella peeps into to obſerve him.</stage>
                     </l>
                     <l>O that I wanted Faith, or could not ſee.</l>
                     <l>Thine-ever-<hi>Alcinda!</hi> my Tongue ſpeaks this,</l>
                     <l>To cheat my Heart; or elſe I hear amiſs.</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Alcinda</hi> falſe! it cannot, ſhall not be;</l>
                     <l>Yet who can doubt, what they ſo plainly ſee?</l>
                     <l>O ſhameleſs Woman! to deſtroy ſo ſoon</l>
                     <l>A happineſs I have ſo hardly won.</l>
                     <l>The wild <hi>Hibernian</hi> Waves, and Winter Air,</l>
                     <l>Are conſtanter than theſe frail Women are:</l>
                     <l>Like thin <hi>Cameleons</hi> ſtill they change their hue,</l>
                     <l>And take freſh flames from ev'ry ſight that's new.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Leon.</speaker>
                     <p>The Fiſh is caught, I muſt allow him line.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fen.</speaker>
                     <p>Hell upon Earth! I'll ſpoil their damn'd deſign.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Leon.</speaker>
                     <p>Now I'll upon him while he looks this way—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fen.</speaker>
                     <p>What, can you run ſo well? I'll make you ſtay.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Leon.</speaker>
                     <l>Mercy dear Sir! Oh Heavens! I'm undone;</l>
                     <l>I ſee my Sentence in your hand,—I'm gone—</l>
                     <l>Ah noble Sir! you know I muſt obey,</l>
                     <l>Puniſh not me, if they have gone aſtray.</l>
                     <l>Gentle Sir pity me! —</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fen.</speaker>
                     <l>Hear me, thou diſmal Meſſenger of Fate!</l>
                     <l>Here, take your Charm, giv't to <hi>Alonzo</hi> ſtrait:</l>
                     <l>If thou betray'ſt me, with one look, or word,</l>
                     <l>Thy Sex ſhall not protect thee from my Sword:</l>
                     <l>Wipe your diſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>mbling eyes, and get you gone,</l>
                     <l>Lo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>k undiſturb'd as if it were unknown.</l>
                     <pb n="55" facs="tcp:199207:32"/>
                     <l>Come Fiend! along, ſee here he comes, take heed:</l>
                     <l>I'll watch you — <stage>Alonzo <hi>enters.</hi>
                        </stage>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Leon.</speaker>
                     <p>Fear me not. I'll do the deed.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fen.</speaker>
                     <l>This may be yet a damn'd malicious plot,</l>
                     <l>'Till he confirm it, I believe it not <stage>Feniſe <hi>hides himſelf.</hi>
                        </stage>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Alon.</speaker>
                     <l>Ha! welcome Loves pretty Envoy!</l>
                     <l>Muſt this Night make us happy? Muſt we go?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Leon.</speaker>
                     <p>There's my bus'neſs, if that inform you ſo.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>She gives him another Letter.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Alon.</speaker>
                     <l>I will not fail, let this engage thee mine.</l>
                     <l>My Service to my Miſtriſs—</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Exeunt</hi> Alonzo <hi>and</hi> Leonella <hi>ſeverally.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fen.</speaker>
                     <l>So, to thine,</l>
                     <l>That is, <hi>Alcinda;</hi> Ah falſe perjur'd Friend!</l>
                     <l>Thy heart ſhall bleed for this e'r this Night end.</l>
                     <l>I'll watch thee to thy Saint, before her Eyes,</l>
                     <l>Thou ſhalt be puniſh'd for thy Perjuries.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Exit</hi> Feniſe.</stage>
               </div>
               <trailer>The End of the Fourth Act.</trailer>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="act">
               <head>ACT V.</head>
               <div n="1" type="scene">
                  <head>Scene 1.</head>
                  <stage>Don Manuel<hi>'s Hall.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Enter</hi> Mingo <hi>and</hi> Leonella.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mingo.</speaker>
                     <l>ABove my higheſt hope! it needs muſt hit,</l>
                     <l>I love thy Beauty, and adore thy Wit:</l>
                     <l>But we muſt try to ſend their Men aſide,</l>
                     <l>They'l ſooner fall, if we their force divide:</l>
                     <l>Though both are Cowards, yet for thy Loves ſake,</l>
                     <l>Any ſtrange Project they will undertake.</l>
                     <l>Can'ſt think of no Deſign? no little Plot?</l>
                     <l>Hell take 'em Hounds! they are not worth a Thought.</l>
                     <l>But it muſt be —</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Leon.</speaker>
                     <l>O that's already done.</l>
                     <pb n="56" facs="tcp:199207:33"/>
                     <l>They are, by this time, in ſo great a fright,</l>
                     <l>They'l have no ſenſe to trouble us to night.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ming.</speaker>
                     <l>Thou'ſt Policy enough to rule a State:</l>
                     <l>Let's to our bus'neſs, for the Night grows late.</l>
                     <l>Fail not to be i'th' Summer-houſe, adieu!</l>
                     <l>I muſt not any more be ſeen with you,</l>
                     <l>For fear of old <hi>Tereſa</hi>'s jealous Head.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Leon.</speaker>
                     <l>But, when my Ladies ask me how I ſped,</l>
                     <l>What ſhall I anſwer them? you know they meant</l>
                     <l>To fly this Night, and therefore was I ſent.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ming.</speaker>
                     <l>Say they'l attend them, and 'tis ten to one</l>
                     <l>They'l put up all their Jewels to be gone.</l>
                     <l>Where to ſecure them, and how, you know.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Leon,</speaker>
                     <p>'Tis done, my Dear! But whither ſhall we go?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ming.</speaker>
                     <l>The time's too ſhort to tell, nor need you ask,</l>
                     <l>Leave that to me, 't has been my chiefeſt Task</l>
                     <l>To ſet you on your way; your Paſport's made, <stage>
                           <hi>Exit</hi> Leonella.</stage>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Charon</hi> ſhall drag you to the <hi>Stygian</hi> Shade.</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Pluto</hi> will get a Cooler for your Luſt,</l>
                     <l>There's roaring Company, and go you muſt.</l>
                     <l>Ive taken care you ſhall not go alone—</l>
                     <l>O what a gallant plotting Rogue I'm grown!</l>
                     <l>I kill but five to night; 'tis true, my hand</l>
                     <l>Is unconcern'd, I do it by command:</l>
                     <l>Like ſtately Tyrants, on my pow'rful Breath</l>
                     <l>Depends the Thred of Life, the Key of Death.</l>
                     <l>Suppoſe I fall, if Hell payes me a Shame,</l>
                     <l>Yet ſhall I leave an everlaſting Name.</l>
                     <l>The hour draws on apace, the Moon ſhines bright,</l>
                     <l>I'll ſtain her Horns with Blood if all hit right. <stage>
                           <hi>Exit</hi> Mingo.</stage>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="scene">
                  <head>Scene 2.</head>
                  <stage>In the Field.</stage>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Enter</hi> Laraſco <hi>loaden with ridiculous Armour.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Leon.</speaker>
                     <l>The hour is paſt, and yet ſhe does not come;</l>
                     <l>My Heart fails me — O that I were at home!</l>
                     <pb n="57" facs="tcp:199207:33"/>
                     <l>Yes, I do love her, and this Act does ſhow't,</l>
                     <l>Do I not hazard here my naked Throat?</l>
                     <l>For ought I know, it may be Planet ſtrook:</l>
                     <l>Heav'ns! it thunders; no 'twas my Armour ſhook.</l>
                     <l>I would go home but for the noiſe I make:</l>
                     <l>What dreadful Acts we Lovers undertake?</l>
                     <l>Ha! what's that purſues me? a Spright! a Spright!</l>
                     <l>It follows me, I ſhall be kill'd this Night,</l>
                     <l>Mercy! ſweet Spright, mercy! It haunts me yet—</l>
                     <l>Yes 'tis my Shadow: I am blind with Sweat.</l>
                     <l>O whoreſon Love! what do I undertake</l>
                     <l>To ſuffer here, for <hi>Leonella's</hi> ſake!</l>
                     <l>Din but a wandring Child now ask the way,</l>
                     <l>Or harmleſs Sheep paſs by that's gone aſtray,</l>
                     <l>Were this true Cannon proof, down muſt it lye,</l>
                     <l>My Sword and all, I ſhould the faſter fly.</l>
                     <l>O Death! a Lyon roars, farewell my Friend!</l>
                     <l>Ha! 'tis a Beetle; ſurely ſhe intends</l>
                     <l>To murther me, elſe why ſhould I ſtay here,</l>
                     <l>Like ſtout Knight-errant, and no Creature near.</l>
                     <l>Now if I could but pray—</l>
                     <l>But how can ſuch poor Rogues as I come to't?</l>
                     <l>When Gentlemen themſelves now cannot do't.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Enter</hi> Sanchez <hi>in a Shroud.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Sanc.</speaker>
                     <l>If ſhe were come, 'twould be a pleaſant Night;</l>
                     <l>No noiſe ſtirring! I'm in a woful fright!</l>
                     <l>All in a clammy ſweat; did ſhe not ſwear,</l>
                     <l>At ten preciſely ſhe would meet me here?</l>
                     <l>Well <hi>Sanchez!</hi> if ſome Brother Spright ſhould come</l>
                     <l>To ſcrape Acquaintance, and conduct thee home;</l>
                     <l>Some Lovers meagre Ghoſt, ſome crafty Fiend,</l>
                     <l>Should by thy Garb miſtake thee for a Friend;</l>
                     <l>Think thee ſome idle Spirit, and command</l>
                     <l>Thee down to darkneſs, how could'ſt thou withſtand?</l>
                     <l>Danger from Men, I think I need not fear,</l>
                     <l>I fright my very ſelf—Ha! who's this here?</l>
                     <pb n="58" facs="tcp:199207:34"/>
                     <l>In Arms from head to foot! then I'm betrai'd,</l>
                     <l>Drawn to my Ruine by this wicked Maid.</l>
                     <l>Falſe deluding Woman! is this thy Love?</l>
                     <l>Didſt thou not vow to meet me in this Grove?</l>
                     <l>I may ſteal off, he has not ſeen me yet—</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Lar.</speaker>
                     <l>Fear won't let me pray; Ha! the noiſe of feet!</l>
                     <l>Oh the Devil! the Devil!</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Sanch.</speaker>
                     <p>Where! where! where!</p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Laraſco <hi>runs out, and</hi> Sanchez <hi>after him.</hi>
                  </stage>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="scene">
                  <head>Scene 3.</head>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Enter</hi> Mingo <hi>alone.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mingo.</speaker>
                     <l>'Tis late, <hi>Alonzo</hi> does not yet appear;</l>
                     <l>He promis'd faithfully he would be here.</l>
                     <l>I hear him coming —</l>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>Enter</hi> Alonzo.</stage>
                     <l>Sir! you are fairly met —</l>
                     <l>This Credit does increaſe your Servants Debt.</l>
                     <l>Pardon my boldneſs Sir! before you go,</l>
                     <l>I will diſcharge part of the Debt I ow.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Alon.</speaker>
                     <l>Honeſt <hi>Mingo!</hi> although I cannot gueſs</l>
                     <l>Thy earneſt bus'neſs, I believe no leſs;</l>
                     <l>I will reward thy care, now ſpeak it out—</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Min.</speaker>
                     <l>The Story is ſo ſtrange, that I much doubt</l>
                     <l>Your want of Faith; and wiſh withall my heart,</l>
                     <l>That I had better tidings to impart.</l>
                     <l>Call all that's Man about you, this will make</l>
                     <l>The ſtrongeſt of your Reſolutions ſhake.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Alon.</speaker>
                     <p>Thy ſtrange beginning makes me fear the end.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Min.</speaker>
                     <l>Y'are cheated by a Miſtriſs, and a Friend:</l>
                     <l>They both are falſe—</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Alon.</speaker>
                     <l>Malicious Fool beware:</l>
                     <l>Think not to take me in a jealous Snare.</l>
                     <pb n="59" facs="tcp:199207:34"/>
                     <l>Thou ly'ſt, nor did a Mortal meet with two</l>
                     <l>Such bleſſings as they are; ſo kind, ſo true:</l>
                     <l>Repeat it not again, this I forgive;</l>
                     <l>After a ſecond blaſphemy thou ſhalt not live.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Min.</speaker>
                     <l>So, this is my reward. What will you do?</l>
                     <l>Pray draw upon your Servant, kill me too.</l>
                     <l>Yet I'll pronounce it true, and on your Sword,</l>
                     <l>My loſs of life ſhall juſtifie my word.</l>
                     <l>This night he takes her with her own conſent,</l>
                     <l>Yet truſt me not, ſwear they are innocent:</l>
                     <l>Your Faith's at liberty—Yet go but home,</l>
                     <l>And kill me there, if <hi>Feniſe</hi> does not come.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Alon.</speaker>
                     <l>Take heed! I take thy word; but if he do,</l>
                     <l>I'll kill that faithleſs Friend, and cheriſh you.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Min.</speaker>
                     <l>You need not kill him Sir! that's too ſevere,</l>
                     <l>He may repent it when he meets you there.</l>
                     <l>Remember Sir! his Faith ne'r knew a Crime,</l>
                     <l>Nor wandring thought, till this unhappy time.</l>
                     <l>Will you deſtroy a Friend ſo often prov'd,</l>
                     <l>Becauſe your Miſtriſs has ſo falſely lov'd?</l>
                     <l>Perhaps the Lady firſt began to Wooe;</l>
                     <l>'Tis not ſo ſtrange, to find their Sex untrue.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Alon.</speaker>
                     <l>No more! th'aſt rais'd an Earthquake in my breaſt,</l>
                     <l>But through his Blood, I know no way to reſt.</l>
                     <l>Yet I would ſpare him, but the Crime's too foul,</l>
                     <l>A ſtrange Convulſion tears my wav'ring Soul:</l>
                     <l>'Tis but a faithleſs Woman at the moſt,</l>
                     <l>She ſoon was won, and is as quickly loſt.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Min.</speaker>
                     <l>He cools too faſt, I muſt renew his heat;</l>
                     <l>This brave Reſolve has made you truly great,</l>
                     <l>Perhaps they'l glory in their baſe ſucceſs,</l>
                     <l>And call your Mercy ſtupid Eaſineſs—</l>
                     <l>But let them laugh; your Conſcience ſtill is clear.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Alon.</speaker>
                     <l>Friendſhip be gone! thou haſt no int'reſt here.</l>
                     <l>Yet, witneſs Heaven! how unwillingly</l>
                     <l>I take his Life, for He (or I) muſt dye.</l>
                     <l>'Tis Honour murthers him, that gilded Air,</l>
                     <l>No other way remains to keep it fair.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <pb n="60" facs="tcp:199207:35"/>
                     <speaker>Min.</speaker>
                     <p>Pray think again</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Alon.</speaker>
                     <p>I've thought too much, away!—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Min.</speaker>
                     <p>Thou wilt repent thy raſhneſs e'r 'tis day. <stage>Aſide.</stage>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Exeunt</hi> Alonzo <hi>and</hi> Mingo.</stage>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Enter</hi> Feniſe as watching them.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fen.</speaker>
                     <l>That baſe contriving Eunuch leads him on;</l>
                     <l>Well Renegado! we ſhall meet anon.</l>
                     <l>Ye Gods! —</l>
                     <l>But why ſhould I invoke your partial aid?</l>
                     <l>By whoſe permiſſion 'tis that I'm betray'd?</l>
                     <l>Theſe little Crimes of perjur'd Love, you ſlight,</l>
                     <l>That you may puniſh them—</l>
                     <l>I know your aim, Revenge is your delight.</l>
                     <l>But ſince you uſe me thus, I'll ſeize your right,</l>
                     <l>I will not for your drowzy Juſtice wait,</l>
                     <l>Ev'n now your Vengeance I'le anticipate.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Ezit</hi> Feniſe <hi>with his Sword drawn.</hi>
                  </stage>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="scene">
                  <head>Scene 4.</head>
                  <stage>A Summer-houſe in a Garden.</stage>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Enter</hi> Don Manuel <hi>alone.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Man.</speaker>
                     <l>In this cloſe Summer-houſe, I keep my State,</l>
                     <l>And like a Prince, diſpoſe of others Fate.</l>
                     <l>My General ſtout <hi>Mingo</hi> takes the care</l>
                     <l>To manage my Affairs of Peace, and War:</l>
                     <l>If any danger ſprings, from blood that's ſpilt,</l>
                     <l>I ſhall the profit reap, and he the guilt.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Enter</hi> Leonella <hi>with a Cabinet.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Leon.</speaker>
                     <l>What mutt'ring voice is that which ſtrikes my Ear?</l>
                     <l>O my unhappy Fate! <hi>Don Manuel</hi> here!</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <pb n="61" facs="tcp:199207:35"/>
                     <speaker>Man.</speaker>
                     <l>Is your bus'neſs to me Lady? Let's ſee,</l>
                     <l>What have you here? pray ſpare your modeſty;</l>
                     <l>This is too troubleſome for you to bear,</l>
                     <l>Deliver up your Charge, and walk in here.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Exeunt</hi> Manuel <hi>and</hi> Leonella.</stage>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Enter</hi> Tereſa <hi>with a Piſtol in one hand, and a Dagger in t'other.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ter.</speaker>
                     <l>Are you ſo nimble? are your Bloods ſo hot?</l>
                     <l>Here's Coolers for you—Theſe will marr your Plot.</l>
                     <l>O my dear <hi>Mingo!</hi> that thou could'ſt but ſee,</l>
                     <l>What dangers I deſpiſe to merit thee.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Exit</hi> Tereſa <hi>after</hi> Man. <hi>and</hi> Leon.</stage>
               </div>
               <div n="5" type="scene">
                  <head>Scene 5.</head>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Enter</hi> Alonzo <hi>and</hi> Mingo.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Min.</speaker>
                     <l>This way he'll come —</l>
                     <l>Pray Sir! think on the ſacred name of Friend,</l>
                     <l>May this ſad difference have a happy end.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Alon.</speaker>
                     <l>Ha! here he comes! be gone! by Heav'n 'tis he,</l>
                     <l>My ſeeming Friend: Good <hi>Mingo</hi> pardon me;</l>
                     <l>I'll ſtudy how to recompence thy care.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Min.</speaker>
                     <p>In your ſucceſs my pains rewarded are.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Exit</hi> Mingo, <hi>but returns again, watching them with his drawn Sword.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Enter</hi> Feniſe.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fen.</speaker>
                     <p>O have I found thee Traytor!</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Alon.</speaker>
                     <l>Sir no words —</l>
                     <l>Our diffrence hears no Umpire but our Swords.</l>
                     <stage>They fight.</stage>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Min.</speaker>
                     <l>peeping. Bravely fought Boyes! So, that thruſt was home,</l>
                     <l>When one is fall'n, then does bold <hi>Mingo</hi> come.</l>
                     <pb n="62" facs="tcp:199207:36"/>
                     <l>I'll ſoon diſpatch the other; how, not yet? <stage>Alonzo <hi>diſarms</hi> Feniſe.</stage>
                     </l>
                     <l>Sure they'r immortal, that was kindly met:</l>
                     <l>Miſchief! what damn'd luck have I? his Sword's loſt.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fen.</speaker>
                     <p>O my curſt fortune—Truth is ever croſt.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Alon.</speaker>
                     <l>Now, if th'haſt any thing to ſay make haſt;</l>
                     <l>But know this very Minute is thy laſt.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fen.</speaker>
                     <l>Uſe thy advantage, kill me, do baſe man!</l>
                     <l>I will have Juſtice when we meet again:</l>
                     <l>There thou ſhalt ſuffer for thy treachery,</l>
                     <l>And that falſe Woman too for whom I die.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Alon.</speaker>
                     <l>What means this language Sir? did I not wooe</l>
                     <l>Thy Miſtriſs for thee, and obtain her too?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fen.</speaker>
                     <l>Muſt I hear this and live! no way to die!</l>
                     <l>Do'ſt thou upbraid me with thy Villany?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Alon.</speaker>
                     <l>Thy Crime does in thy ill ſucceſs appear;</l>
                     <l>Did'ſt thou not come to meet <hi>Roſella</hi> here?</l>
                     <l>I knew thy foul intent, I knew it well,</l>
                     <l>What Charms did'ſt thou imploy? what curſed Spell,</l>
                     <l>To rob me of her Heart? What canſt thou ſay?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fen.</speaker>
                     <l>Thou kill'ſt me ten times o're in this delay.</l>
                     <l>Pr'y thee diſpatch, leſt I ſome bluſhes ſhow,</l>
                     <l>To think thoſe Crimes, thou canſt not bluſh to do.</l>
                     <l>Let me not ſtand a Witneſs to my ſhame,</l>
                     <l>Since you, to meet the falſe <hi>Alcinda</hi> came.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Alon.</speaker>
                     <p>Then we are both abus'd —</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ming.</speaker>
                     <l>O helliſh ſpight!</l>
                     <l>Yet I'll get ſomething, if the reſt hit right. <stage>
                           <hi>Exit</hi> Mingo.</stage>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fen.</speaker>
                     <l>Abus'd! am I awake? did I not ſee,</l>
                     <l>When <hi>Leonella</hi> gave a note to thee?</l>
                     <l>A Letter from <hi>Alcinda?</hi> and when you</l>
                     <l>Vow'd not to fail, Ha! is not this true?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Alon.</speaker>
                     <l>That very Letter you may here peruſe.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Feniſe <hi>takes the Letter and reads it.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
                     <body>
                        <head>To Signior <hi>Alonzo.</hi>
                        </head>
                        <l>My breaſt is loaded with unhappy News,</l>
                        <l>Which onely in your Ears I dare relate;</l>
                        <l>If y<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>u vouchſafe your preſence when 'tis late,</l>
                        <pb n="63" facs="tcp:199207:36"/>
                        <l>Conceal it from your Friend, and come alone;</l>
                        <l>Elſe you will loſe, and I ſhall be undone.</l>
                        <closer>
                           <signed>
                              <hi>Your Slave</hi> Mingo.</signed>
                        </closer>
                     </body>
                  </floatingText>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fen.</speaker>
                     <l>O ſubtle Villain! And thou crafty Maid!</l>
                     <l>What have I done? That I ſhould be betraid?</l>
                     <l>I fear this is not all,—ſure they intend</l>
                     <l>Some miſchief to the Ladies e're it end.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Alon.</speaker>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Mingo</hi> juſt parted hence, we may with ſpeed</l>
                     <l>Prevent all danger, 'sdeath how faſt you bleed?</l>
                     <l>Forgive my raſh belief! —</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fen.</speaker>
                     <l>I muſt from you</l>
                     <l>The ſame entreat: But let's the Rogue purſue—</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Alon.</speaker>
                     <l>He ſhall not 'ſcape, I'm ſure he went this way.</l>
                     <l>My fears grow ſtronger by the leaſt delay. <stage>A Piſtol fir'd within.</stage>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fen.</speaker>
                     <p>Ha! a Piſtol! I fear we are too late.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Alon.</speaker>
                     <l>We will prevent, or we'll revenge their Fate.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Exeunt</hi> Alonzo <hi>and</hi> Feniſe.</stage>
               </div>
               <div n="6" type="scene">
                  <head>Scene 6.</head>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Enter</hi> Manuel <hi>wounded.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Man.</speaker>
                     <l>Oh cruel Witch! inhumane Sorcereſs!</l>
                     <l>I'm pepper'd now for all my wickedneſs:</l>
                     <l>Incarnate Devil! for my Ruine ſent!</l>
                     <l>All Curſes Men and Devils can invent,</l>
                     <l>And mine beſides, fall on thy bloody Heart—</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Enter</hi> Tereſa <hi>with a Dagger in her hand, dragging in</hi> Leonella.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ter.</speaker>
                     <l>Come! come along, I'll teach you a new Art</l>
                     <l>To couple; do ye roar in conſort now?</l>
                     <l>Dry'd Dog! I was not good enough for you:</l>
                     <l>Would ye be yoak'd? I'll ſee ye yoak'd, I will,</l>
                     <l>You ſhall be joyn'd; what are you roaring ſtill?</l>
                     <l>Silence! and hear your heavy Doom: Now Dame!</l>
                     <l>Now bold Huſſey! was there no other Game?</l>
                     <pb n="64" facs="tcp:199207:37"/>
                     <l>No Pipe but mine to make you dance? I'll try</l>
                     <l>Who ſhall be Miſtriſs now, of you or I.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Leon.</speaker>
                     <p>Dear Madam! O Heav'ns! hear what I can ſay —</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ter.</speaker>
                     <l>Noble <hi>Signior!</hi> pray bow your head this way,</l>
                     <l>See your Ven'ſon quarter'd, and when that's done,</l>
                     <l>With you I'll finiſh what I have begun.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Man.</speaker>
                     <l>My Royal <hi>Donna!</hi> dear <hi>Tereſa</hi> hold!</l>
                     <l>I'll be thy Slave—</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ter.</speaker>
                     <l>Poor Fool! thou art too old:</l>
                     <l>In Prayers ſpend thy time, for 'tis but ſhort,</l>
                     <l>Or curſe me if thou wilt, I care not for't.</l>
                     <l>Have at thee—</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Enter</hi> Laraſco <hi>running in his Armour, and</hi> Perez <hi>following him in his Shroud.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Lar.</speaker>
                     <p>Oh a Ghoſt! a Ghoſt away!—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Perez.</speaker>
                     <p>No Ghoſt! I am no Ghoſt! good Neighbors ſtay—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>All run off in a fright,</hi> Perez <hi>purſuing them.</hi>
                  </stage>
               </div>
               <div n="7" type="scene">
                  <head>Scene 7.</head>
                  <stage>Don Manuel<hi>'s Houſe.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Enter</hi> Mingo <hi>with Bags of Money.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ming.</speaker>
                     <l>Now Fortune, if thou haſt not ſworn my fall,</l>
                     <l>Grant me one happy hour, and have at all.</l>
                     <l>The Houſe is yet my own; and here's my Mint —</l>
                     <l>If all my Plots ſhould fail; the Devil's in't. <stage>
                           <hi>Exit</hi> Mingo.</stage>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Enter</hi> Alcinda <hi>and</hi> Roſella.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Alc.</speaker>
                     <l>Now Madam! does the tedious time draw nigh,</l>
                     <l>When we ſhall have our long wiſh'd Liberty.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Roſ.</speaker>
                     <l>May this bleſt Night, like ſome auſpicious Star,</l>
                     <l>Shine bright in Fames Eternal Calendar.</l>
                     <l>May it produce no ſad unhappy Birth,</l>
                     <l>But be to all the World a Night of Mirth.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <pb n="65" facs="tcp:199207:37"/>
                     <speaker>Alc.</speaker>
                     <l>May after times, when they would ſum their bliſs,</l>
                     <l>Wiſh happy Dayes, and all their Nights like this.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Enter</hi> Mingo.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ming.</speaker>
                     <l>This way, your Servants wonder at your ſtay —</l>
                     <l>The watchful Cock foretells approaching day.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Roſel.</speaker>
                     <p>Good <hi>Mingo!</hi> lead the way; how my heart beats?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Alc.</speaker>
                     <l>This little trouble all our joy compleats.</l>
                     <l>What noiſe is that? <stage>A noiſe at the dore.</stage>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ming.</speaker>
                     <p>Hell! they have forc'd the dore—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Alc.</speaker>
                     <p>If Fate frown now, I'll never truſt it more.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Roſel.</speaker>
                     <p>That noiſe has made me fear we are undone.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ming.</speaker>
                     <p>Yet, through this other dore we may be gone.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Mingo <hi>going out, meets</hi> Feniſe <hi>and</hi> Alonzo, <hi>with their Swords drawn.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ming.</speaker>
                     <p>Then to my laſt ſhift— <stage>He draws a pair of Piſtols.</stage>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Alon.</speaker>
                     <l>Sir! y' are fairly met —</l>
                     <l>This favor does encreaſe your Servants debt.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ming.</speaker>
                     <p>Not ſo well met as you imagine yet.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Alon.</speaker>
                     <l>Yes Hell-hound! you are;</l>
                     <l>And ere you part, I will reward your care,</l>
                     <l>Your care to ruin us — thou canſt not fly.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ming.</speaker>
                     <p>If you but ſtir a foot, they both ſhall dye. <stage>He preſents the Piſtols.</stage>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fen.</speaker>
                     <p>Inhuman Dog!</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ming.</speaker>
                     <l>Good words, ſtand further yet—</l>
                     <l>What I have done, I need not now repeat.</l>
                     <l>I know you'll kill me, but before I dye,</l>
                     <l>I'll make you ſharers in my miſery.</l>
                     <l>Your Miſtriſſes ſhall lead the way: D' ye ſtare!</l>
                     <l>Their Deſtinies within my power are;</l>
                     <l>And thus I'll ruine them—</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fen.</speaker>
                     <l>Hold! good Rogue hold!</l>
                     <l>We'll be thy Slaves, thou ſhalt have Mines of Gold.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ming.</speaker>
                     <l>A Kingdom ſhall not buy one hours delay:</l>
                     <l>Yet, to torment you more, a while I'll ſtay.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <pb n="66" facs="tcp:199207:38"/>
                     <speaker>Alon.</speaker>
                     <l>Art thou ſo heartleſs<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and ſo childiſh grown,</l>
                     <l>To fight with Women? when this Act is known,</l>
                     <l>Thou wilt be branded with a Cowards name,</l>
                     <l>A fearful Rogue, Art thou ſo loſt to ſhame?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fen.</speaker>
                     <l>So loſt to policy?</l>
                     <l>For if to miſchief th'art ſo firmly bent,</l>
                     <l>By killing us thou may'ſt thy death prevent.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ming.</speaker>
                     <p>That's well advis'd —</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Roſel.</speaker>
                     <l>I dare thy ſharpeſt ſpight, and will not grieve</l>
                     <l>To dye, ſo my <hi>Alonzo</hi> may but live.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Alc.</speaker>
                     <p>See what thou doeſt, thou bloody Devil! do!</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Min.</speaker>
                     <p>Seal up your lips, or I'll begin with you.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Alc.</speaker>
                     <l>Brave Villain do! I will requite thy pain,</l>
                     <l>If ſpight won't make thee ſhoot, yet do't for gain.</l>
                     <l>Here's Gold and Jewels, if theſe will not do,</l>
                     <l>I'll call thee Coward; nay I'll curſe thee too.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Min.</speaker>
                     <l>No more! I'll quickly end this Generous ſtrife.</l>
                     <l>Theſe Ladies never injur'd me, 'tis true,</l>
                     <l>But I'll kill them, to be reveng'd of you.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>He flaſhes in the pan; and</hi> Alonzo <hi>and</hi> Feniſe <hi>diſarm him.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Alon.</speaker>
                     <p>Thou cruel Rogue! now we'll command thy fate.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Min.</speaker>
                     <l>I will not beg your love, nor fear your hate.</l>
                     <l>Had not my fooliſh pity ſtaid my hand,</l>
                     <l>My Life had never been at your command.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>A great noiſe within.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Roſel.</speaker>
                     <p>Ano<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>her Storm begins, ere this is gone.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Alc.</speaker>
                     <p>If 'tis your Father, we are yet undone.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>
                        <hi>Laraſco</hi> within.</speaker>
                     <p>For pity's ſake let's in, who ere you be.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fen.</speaker>
                     <p>That's my Raſcal's voice.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>
                        <hi>Lar.</hi> within.</speaker>
                     <p>Ay Sir! 'tis me! 'tis me! <stage>
                           <hi>Enter</hi> Laraſco <hi>arm'd.</hi>
                        </stage>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fen.</speaker>
                     <p>What does this folly mean?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Lar.</speaker>
                     <l>O Sir! as I to meet my Love did go forth,</l>
                     <l>The very Devil follow'd me; and ſo forth—</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Enter</hi> Manuel, Leonella, Tereſa, <hi>falling over one another for haſte— followed by</hi> Sanchez <hi>in a Shroud—</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Alon.</speaker>
                     <l>What tricks are theſe?</l>
                     <pb n="67" facs="tcp:199207:38"/>
                     <l>Speak Devil! or I'll kill thee if I can.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>San.</speaker>
                     <p>Hold! good Sir hold! I am your very Man. <stage>Pulls off his Shroud.</stage>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Leon.</speaker>
                     <p>There's the Original of all this Rout.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ming.</speaker>
                     <l>Were ever things ſo croſly brought about?</l>
                     <l>Nay Sir 'tis true; and had my Plots hit right,</l>
                     <l>There had not one of you ſurviv'd this Night.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Roſel.</speaker>
                     <p>O my dear Father! —</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ming.</speaker>
                     <l>Lady you miſtake, nay I'll make you known:</l>
                     <l>Since I am loſt, I will not fall alone.</l>
                     <l>He's not your Father, he's a Rogue, a Cheat,</l>
                     <l>He is in nothing, but in Miſchief, great.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Man.</speaker>
                     <l>Malicious Rogue! dear Daughter hear him not:</l>
                     <l>He's raving mad now he has miſs'd his Plot.</l>
                     <l>Dear Child lead me to Bed, I'm very ſick —</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ming.</speaker>
                     <l>To Bed! to th' Gallows; this is a meer trick,</l>
                     <l>To get off—</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Roſel.</speaker>
                     <p>Let him not uſe my Father ſo —</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ming.</speaker>
                     <p>Madam! he's a Villain, and your mortal Foe.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Alon.</speaker>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Mingo</hi> ſpeak out, what is it thou canſt ſay?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Tereſ.</speaker>
                     <p>Damn'd Lyes! miſchievous Lyes! lead him away—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ming.</speaker>
                     <l>Woman hear thy Charge—</l>
                     <l>My Crime's ſo great, and ſo prodigious grown,</l>
                     <l>Though I beg pardon, I can hope for none.</l>
                     <l>But when their faults in competition come,</l>
                     <l>Mine are but Cyphers, theirs a total Sum.</l>
                     <l>Had you not Siſters once, whom you think loſt?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fen.</speaker>
                     <p>Nay, more than think, we know that they were drown'd.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ming.</speaker>
                     <l>Sir? ſpare your Sighs, the Ladies ſoon are found.</l>
                     <l>When <hi>Don Valaſco</hi> your brave Father dy'd,</l>
                     <l>You being too young to be your Siſters Guide,</l>
                     <l>Were left with her, to noble <hi>Pedro</hi>'s care;</l>
                     <l>Your honour'd Father Sir— <stage>
                           <hi>To</hi> Alonzo.</stage>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fen.</speaker>
                     <p>Thou ſeek'ſt delayes in Story fetch'd ſo far.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Alon.</speaker>
                     <l>All this we know, and how my Father ſtrove,</l>
                     <l>To joyn our Families with Bonds of Love.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fen.</speaker>
                     <l>Then how our Siſters with <hi>Don Pedro</hi> went,</l>
                     <l>When in <hi>Peru</hi> he had a Government:</l>
                     <l>We know the time when they took Ship again,</l>
                     <l>But never heard when they return'd to <hi>Spain.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <pb n="68" facs="tcp:199207:39"/>
                     <speaker>Ming.</speaker>
                     <l>The reſt I can relate, and mean to do,</l>
                     <l>More in Revenge to them, than Love to you.</l>
                     <l>The Sea mov'd gently, and with flatt'ring Gales,</l>
                     <l>The am'rous Wind did court the flying Sails.</l>
                     <l>But Fate, that knows a thouſand paths to Death,</l>
                     <l>Sent a Diſeaſe to take your Father's Breath.</l>
                     <l>To <hi>Sanchez</hi> his old Servant, and a Maid,</l>
                     <l>He left your Siſters, and the Wealth he had;</l>
                     <l>With careful duty, to reſtore again</l>
                     <l>Their Charge to you, when they return'd to <hi>Spain.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>But in the very Port, they met with one</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Gorzell,</hi> a cruel tatter'd Pickaroon;</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Sanchez</hi> they murther'd, made the reſt their prey,</l>
                     <l>And took your Siſters very names away.</l>
                     <l>What they did ſince is partly known to you,</l>
                     <l>None but themſelves know what they meant to do:</l>
                     <l>This is the Villain, that the curſed Maid,</l>
                     <l>By whoſe infernal Plots they were betrai'd:</l>
                     <l>This Womans names <hi>Guttarze,</hi> that Mans <hi>Gorzell,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>By whoſe inhuman hands poor <hi>Sanchez</hi> fell.</l>
                     <l>And thoſe your Siſters are, thoſe Ladies there!</l>
                     <l>What Heav'n decrees, cannot be alter'd here.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Alon.</speaker>
                     <p>O that we could believe thee —</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fen.</speaker>
                     <p>What ſay you?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>
                        <hi>Man.</hi> and <hi>Tereſ.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <p>Mercy! mercy Gentlemen! 'tis too true.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Alon.</speaker>
                     <p>Which is my Siſter? which muſt be my Bride?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Tereſ.</speaker>
                     <l>Y'have fix'd thoſe Knots your Father long ſince ty'd;</l>
                     <l>Madam <hi>Alcinda,</hi> Sir, your Siſter is,</l>
                     <l>And you <hi>Roſella</hi> are <hi>Don Fenis</hi>'s.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fen.</speaker>
                     <l>Exceſs of happineſs! thy Life's thy own, <stage>
                           <hi>To</hi> Mingo</stage>
                     </l>
                     <l>Dangers ſo great, ſo ſuddenly o'reblown,</l>
                     <l>Make all our joyes like pleaſing Dreams appear.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Roſel.</speaker>
                     <l>I cannot look this way without a Tear.</l>
                     <l>Can I ſee him, I once call'd Father, kneel,</l>
                     <l>And weep to me?—</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Alc.</speaker>
                     <p>Methinks I fear him ſtill.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Roſel.</speaker>
                     <p>You ſhall forgive him—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Alon.</speaker>
                     <l>The greateſt Injuries were yours; if you</l>
                     <l>Can pardon them, with all my Heart I do.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <pb n="69" facs="tcp:199207:39"/>
                     <speaker>Fen.</speaker>
                     <l>But we forget the blackeſt Crime they did,</l>
                     <l>Although we pardon them, for that they'll bleed.</l>
                     <l>Poor murther'd <hi>Sanchez</hi> does for Vengeance cry,</l>
                     <l>The Law will ſeize them, and for that they'll dye.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Man.</speaker>
                     <l>Cruel Woman! had not thy reſtleſs Will</l>
                     <l>Urg'd on his death, he had been living ſtill.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ter.</speaker>
                     <l>Thou fooliſh Man! why wouldſt thou hear me then?</l>
                     <l>Nature allows our Sex leſs Wit than Men,</l>
                     <l>That you may rule us when we go aſide;</l>
                     <l>Had I been govern'd, <hi>Sanchez</hi> had not dy'd.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Roſel.</speaker>
                     <p>No other wayes to ſave their lives? pray try.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Sanch.</speaker>
                     <l>Madam! there is, this time they ſhall not dye.</l>
                     <l>Look on me well, have you not known this Face?</l>
                     <l>Time has not chang'd it much from what it was.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Man.</speaker>
                     <p>'Tis he! 'tis he! good <hi>Sanchez</hi> pardon me.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ter.</speaker>
                     <l>O <hi>Sanchez!</hi> we confeſs our cruelty:</l>
                     <l>Pray forgive us—</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Sanch.</speaker>
                     <l>May your forgiveneſs be,</l>
                     <l>From all the World as hearty as from me.</l>
                     <l>Since I have ſeen my Miſtriſſes again,</l>
                     <l>No more remembrance of my Wounds remain.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fen.</speaker>
                     <l>Then you are free, but ere this Sun goes down,</l>
                     <l>We charge ye every one to leave the Town.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Alon.</speaker>
                     <l>Where we reſide be never ſeen again,</l>
                     <l>The Law ſhall ſeize ye if we meet in <hi>Spain.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ming.</speaker>
                     <l>Pox o' thy trembling Paw! hadſt thou but dy'd,</l>
                     <l>Or done thy work, I had been ſatisfi'd.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ter.</speaker>
                     <l>Curſe on thy plotting pate, and wheedling tongue,</l>
                     <l>Hadſt thou been hang'd we yet had flouriſh'd long.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Leon.</speaker>
                     <p>Hard-hearted <hi>Mingo!</hi> wouldſt thou murther me?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ming.</speaker>
                     <l>No pretty Rogue! I was to marry thee.</l>
                     <l>Save your Lordſhip mighty <hi>Manuel</hi> hight!</l>
                     <l>And eke your fair La-dee <hi>Tereſa</hi> bright.</l>
                     <l>Great <hi>Don!</hi> pray ſhut your Lordly Gate, 'gainſt all</l>
                     <l>Of your own Sex; hate ev'ry thing that's Male.</l>
                     <l>Such tempting traſh would make a Saint grow vain:</l>
                     <l>Take heed no ſmooth face't Eunuch come again —</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Bezo las mannos Signior!</hi>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <pb n="70" facs="tcp:199207:40"/>
                     <speaker>Alon.</speaker>
                     <l>No more!</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Sanchez</hi> I to his former place reſtore.</l>
                     <l>Let's to the Sacred Temple haſte, and pay</l>
                     <l>Glad thanks to Heaven for this happy day.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fen.</speaker>
                     <l>Let ſmiling <hi>Hymen,</hi> with his Nuptial bands,</l>
                     <l>As we have joyn'd our Hearts, unite our Hands.</l>
                     <l>Now all our Doubts and Fears, with joyes are crown'd,</l>
                     <l>Our Cares are loſt, and our loſt Siſters found.</l>
                  </sp>
               </div>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="epilogue">
            <pb n="71" facs="tcp:199207:40"/>
            <head>EPILOGUE</head>
            <byline>Spoken by Mrs. KNEPPE.</byline>
            <lg>
               <l>VVHen Wit, and Native Beauty found Succeſs,</l>
               <l>Without a daz'ling Scene, or gaudy Dreſs,</l>
               <l>Then Playes were good, and wholeſom your Amour;</l>
               <l>But when theſe downright Bleſſings pleas'd no more,</l>
               <l>Poets, from <hi>France,</hi> fetch'd new Intrigue, and Plot,</l>
               <l>Kind Women, new <hi>French</hi> Words, and Faſhions got:</l>
               <l>And finding all <hi>French</hi> Tricks ſo much did pleaſe,</l>
               <l>'T oblige ye more, They got — ev'n their Diſeaſe.</l>
               <l>That too did take — and as much Honour gets</l>
               <l>As breaking Windows, or not paying Debts.</l>
               <l>O 'tis ſo gente! So modiſh! and ſo fine!</l>
               <l>To ſhrug and cry, Faith <hi>Jack!</hi> I drink no Wine:</l>
               <l>For I've a ſwinging Clap this very time —</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Poets ſaw this, and brought their Stages Crimes,</l>
               <l>Chang'd Comedy to Farce, and Senſe to Rimes.</l>
               <l>That took your very Souls —</l>
               <l>But now, you are ſo ſtrangely hum'rous grown,</l>
               <l>That even theſe, your dear Regalio's will not down:</l>
               <l>The neweſt <hi>Miſs,</hi> with all her little Arts,</l>
               <l>Sometimes can't ſoften your obdurate hearts:</l>
               <l>At other times, you are ſo far from Pride,</l>
               <l>A ſwarthy Gipſie would be deify'd.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Then, to your Friends, you tell ſuch horrid Lyes,</l>
               <l>You had a Pers'n of Honour in diſguiſe!</l>
               <l>Dam'ee the pretty'st Creature! O ſuch Eyes —</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>No Play without a new Machine will do,</l>
               <l>Shortly, Your <hi>Miſs</hi> must act with Engine to:</l>
               <l>For brisk, and pretty, you will cry at laſt,</l>
               <l>Can ſhe Curvet? and is ſhe Thorough-pac't?</l>
               <l>Y'have Fiddle, and Motion now, and all That —</l>
               <l>'Zbud! I wonder what a Devil you'd be at.</l>
               <l>If you perſiſt in theſe lewd damning wayes,</l>
               <l>You'll have no more new <hi>Miſſes;</hi> nor new <hi>Playes.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <closer>
               <signed>Per T. D.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <pb facs="tcp:199207:41"/>
            <head>ERRATA.</head>
            <p>PAge 4. line 23. read <hi>Feniſe</hi> for <hi>Mingo:</hi> p. 14. l. 24. r. <hi>and</hi> for <hi>are:</hi> p. 16. l. 15. r. <hi>Her Sword</hi>—p. 24. l. 6. r. <hi>liv'd here</hi>—p. 29. l. 11. r. <hi>or</hi> for <hi>od:</hi> p. 33. l. 11. r. <hi>ſo baſely</hi>—for <hi>ſo bravely</hi> —p. 41. l. 3. r. <hi>talk</hi> for <hi>take:</hi> l. 33. r. <hi>Sot</hi> for <hi>Scot:</hi> p. 43. l. 1. r. <hi>a</hi> for <hi>her:</hi> p. 45. l. 24. r. <hi>thouſand—Curſes:</hi> l. 31. r. <hi>learn</hi> for <hi>lrarn:</hi> p. 48. l. 14. r. <hi>darted</hi> for <hi>darte:</hi> p. 57. l. 12. r. <hi>did</hi> for <hi>din:</hi> p. 59. l. 1. r. <hi>ne'r</hi> for <hi>nor.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:199207:41"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
